<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information. Change the value of xml:lang if not English.-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to
                    Love Simplicity through the Endings Principles</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo xml:id="martindholmes">
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Martin <dhq:family>Holmes</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3944-1116</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria Humanities Computing and Media
                        Centre</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mholmes@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Martin Holmes is a programmer in the University of Victoria Humanities
                            Computing and Media Centre. He is the lead programmer on several large
                            digital edition projects including the <title rend="italic">Map of Early
                                Modern London</title> (MoEML) and <title rend="italic">Le Mariage
                                sous l'Ancien Régime</title>, and is part of the Project Endings
                            team. He served on the TEI Technical Council from 2010 to 2015 and was
                            managing editor of the <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                                Initiative</title> from 2013 to 2015.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Joey <dhq:family>Takeda</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0440-6062</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Innovation Lab, Simon Fraser
                        University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>takeda@sfu.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Joey Takeda is a Developer in the Digital Humanities Innovation Lab
                            (DHIL) at Simon Fraser University. He holds an MA in English Literature
                            from the University of British Columbia and is currently the Technical
                            Director of <title rend="italic">The Winnifred Eaton Archive</title>.
                            Prior to joining the DHIL, he was the lead programmer for the <title
                                rend="italic">Landscapes of Injustice</title> digital archive and a
                            programmer for <title rend="italic">The Map of Early Modern
                                London</title> and <title rend="italic">Linked Early Modern Drama
                                Online</title>.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">001385</idno>
                <idno type="volume">[to be
                    assigned]<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">[to be
                    assigned]<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date>2022</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!--         If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>digital editions</item>
                        <item>software obsolescence</item>
                        <item>sustainability</item>
                        <item>static websites</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="#martindholmes" when="2022-11">Created the file and encoded the
                text.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the
                    culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have
                    rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and
                    reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal
                    dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how
                    not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set
                    of principles, practices and software tools which we believe provide solid
                    defences against digital extinction. Below, we describe the institutional
                    context within which Project Endings was born, and lay out methodically the
                    guiding principles by which we now develop digital editions and other web
                    resources.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>We’ve made all our digital editions static websites, and should too; you’ll
                    regret it if you don’t.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>From Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks: On Learning to Love Simplicity through the Endings
                Principles</head>
            <!-- Use <div> only if there is more than one section -->
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>

                <p>This article, by two of the technical leads on Project Endings, represents the
                    culmination of all we have learned over the last few years, during which we have
                    rescued over a dozen projects from death by software obsolescence and
                    reconstituted them as entirely static, standalone websites with minimal
                    dependencies. We now know a great deal, mostly from our own mistakes, about how
                    not to build robust, long-lasting digital resources, and we have developed a set
                    of principles, practices and software tools which we believe provide solid
                    defences against digital extinction. Below, we describe the institutional
                    context within which Project Endings was born, and lay out methodically the
                    guiding principles by which we now develop digital editions and other web
                    resources.</p>


            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Early Days</head>

                <p>What is now the Humanities Computing and Media Centre (HCMC) at the University of
                    Victoria was once simply the Language Centre, a unit whose role was to maintain
                    language laboratories and computer workstations and to write software
                    applications used for language teaching courses. We had both Macintosh and
                    Windows workstations, and would typically write custom software for either
                    platform but not both, since writing cross-platform software applications was
                    quite difficult in the days before the World Wide Web (WWW) and Java. When the
                    Web first appeared, we seized on it enthusiastically as a practical way to
                    provide language-teaching resources which could be delivered not only on both
                    kinds of workstation in our labs but also to other locations. When JavaScript
                    emerged around 1996, we were blessed with the capability to create truly
                    interactive programmed teaching exercises, and by the turn of the millenium we
                    had built language-teaching exercise collections for many languages, as well as
                    desktop authoring tools to make the creation of such pages easy for non-coders
                        (<ref target="#arneilHolmes1998">Arneil and Holmes 1998</ref>, <ref
                        target="#arneilHolmes1999">1999</ref>, and <ref target="#arneilHolmes2001"
                        >2001</ref>).</p>

                <p>The materials we created during this period still exist, and they still work
                    perfectly. Examples can be seen in the Indonesian course materials created in
                    1999 (<ptr target="https://web.uvic.ca/hrd/indonesian/"/>) and the
                    endearingly-dated <title rend="quotes">Web Language</title> online presentation
                        (<ptr target="#holmes1997"/>), originally created in 1997 and last updated
                    in 1999. The latter includes a feedback form which is still regularly used, so
                    it still clearly has some relevance despite its appearance. The HTML and
                    JavaScript is still fully functional, although non-standards-based cutting-edge
                    technologies of the time, such as RealAudio, no longer work of course.</p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Screenshot of Beginning Indonesian homepage (left) and exercise (right).
                        Screenshot taken in 2021, but it looked the same in 1999.</head>
                    <graphic url="images/figure01.png" style="width: 1432px; height: 775px;"/>
                    <figDesc>The home page and an example exercise from the Beginning Indonesian
                        site, dating from the late 1990s.</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <p>In the early 2000s, the Language Centre was transformed into the Humanities
                    Computing and Media Centre, and given a wider mandate to support what was then
                    commonly termed Humanities Computing, now Digital Humanities. Better-funded
                    projects came along, and more ambitious coding was undertaken, supporting not
                    only language-teaching resources but also digital edition projects, historical
                    datasets, mapping initiatives, and many other research and teaching activities.
                    In particular, we developed some expertise in TEI and the XML-related languages,
                    and began to create large online document collections such as the <title
                        rend="italic">Colonial Despatches</title> project (<ptr
                        target="https://bcgenesis.uvic.ca/"/>) and <title rend="italic">Le Mariage
                        sous l’Ancien Régime</title> (<ptr target="https://mariage.uvic.ca/"/>). In
                    place of static (albeit interactive) web pages, we started to build more
                    sophisticated web applications based on PHP/MySQL database stacks and the eXist
                    XML database.<note><ptr
                            target="https://www.exist-db.org/exist/apps/homepage/index.html"
                        />.</note> Now blessed with our own server infrastructure thanks to the
                    ground-breaking Canadian TaPOR (Text-Analysis Portal) initiative, we were able
                    to run Tomcat, Cocoon, Postgresql, and a host of other backends to support the
                    growing variety of DH projects under way at our institution.</p>

                <p>These server-side systems enabled us (along with the rest of the DH community) to
                    build resources which were more coherent and easier to maintain; information
                    about a single entity, individual, or place could be encoded or stored in a
                    single record, but retrieved and displayed in a multitude of contexts wherever
                    it was needed. Documents could be transcribed and encoded once, but decorated
                    and rendered in many different ways based on the needs of the user or the
                    application context. Sophisticated searching, grouping, and presentation options
                    were easy to implement. Beginning in 2003 we generated a large number of these
                    projects; our servers were well-populated and their CPUs were busy running
                    XQuery, XSLT, PHP, SQL, and even ASP code.</p>

                <p>As Lou Burnard (<ref target="#burnard2016">2016</ref>) remarks, <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#burnard2016">nothing in digital form is ever really
                        finished.</quote> DH projects may languish untended and unloved for periods
                    of time, but their progenitors typically intend to continue working on them
                    periodically or when funding allows. Setting up such projects implies a
                    commitment to maintaining them, and as our project portfolio burgeoned, so did
                    our maintenance burden. As we moved into the 2010s and onwards, a clear pattern
                    began to emerge: projects created in the 1990s continued to work as intended
                    with virtually no maintenance at all, but the projects we had built on
                    sophisticated backend systems such as MySQL and eXist required frequent and
                    time-consuming maintenance work. As an example, the <title rend="italic">Robert
                        Graves Diary</title> (<ptr target="https://graves.uvic.ca/"/>), one of our
                    earliest digital edition projects, was originally written based on eXist version
                    0.9 in 2003–2004; it had to be steadily revised throughout 2005–2007, and then
                    completely rewritten for eXist 1.4 in 2012, because the original
                    Tomcat/Cocoon/eXist 0.9 stack became obsolete. Then in 2014 it had to be updated
                    again. This was a project on which the core academic work had been completed in
                    the first phase of the project, but due to infrastructure churn it regularly
                    returned to haunt us. Over the years, we amassed a maintenance burden which
                    threatened to overwhelm our ability to support new projects coming through our
                    doors.</p>

                <p>This problem was the impetus for Project Endings. The Web had solved for us the
                    challenge to <quote rend="inline"
                        source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write_once,_run_anywhere">write once,
                        run anywhere</quote>;<note><ptr
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Write_once,_run_anywhere"
                        />.</note> the issue we were now addressing was how to <quote rend="inline"
                        >write once, run forever.</quote> Project Endings brought together a team
                    consisting of academic digital humanists, programmers, and librarians, along
                    with a selection of active, complex digital edition projects, to determine how
                    we could best plan, execute, and archive our projects in such a way that they
                    would live on indefinitely without further maintenance.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>3. A Catalogue of Failures</head>

                <p>In the early days of the Endings project, we began to examine in detail how our
                    older digital editions and sites had progressively broken down. Some problems
                    were obvious: obsolete versions of server-side applications and services
                    (MapServer, MySQL, PHP) had been retired or replaced, and old code would not run
                    on new versions, even if new versions existed. Other failures were more subtle.
                    We investigated, for example, how successfully our applications had been
                    archived by The Internet Archive (<ptr target="https://archive.org/"/>) and
                    reproduced on the Wayback Machine (<ptr target="https://archive.org/web/"/>). It
                    was immediately obvious that sites built on backend databases, where
                        <q>pages</q> were in fact queries to the database, were very problematic.
                    The project <title rend="italic">Le Mariage sous l’Ancien Régime</title>, which
                    linked to its anthology documents using URLs that queried the server (e.g.
                        <code>http://mariage.uvic.ca/xhtml.xq?id=le_bourgeoise_desprit</code>), was
                    scarcely archived at all, presumably because the archive crawler was unable to
                    follow or parse the query-based links successfully, so for the most part, the
                    archived versions of the site consist mainly of notices that <quote
                        rend="inline">The Wayback Machine has not archived that URL.</quote></p>

                <figure>
                    <head>Wayback Machine error page</head>
                    <graphic url="images/figure02.png" style="width: ; height: ;"/>
                    <figDesc>An error page from the Wayback Machine, which has failed to archive a
                        web page whose content is retrieved using a query string.</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <p><title rend="italic">Mariage</title> also had a rather gratuitous feature whereby
                    the end user could choose between three available colour schemes, and because
                    that functionality relied entirely on JavaScript, the required CSS files had
                    been retrieved and stored as though they were HTML pages, and no styling
                    appeared on the site pages at all. Site search engines failed completely, as did
                    any annotation popups linked from texts which relied on retrieving data by
                    querying the backend database, and JavaScript-based interactivity was generally
                    broken. In fact, the majority of our large-scale, high-profile digital edition
                    projects were scarcely functional at all in the Wayback Machine, and most of
                    their content had not even been retrieved and stored.</p>

                <p>The Internet Archive had never been one of our primary backup strategies, but it
                    was disappointing to discover how unsuccessful it had been in its attempts to
                    crawl and reproduce our sites. Although some of these failures could perhaps be
                    laid at the door of the Internet Archive crawler, Heritrix, which had some
                    limitations, most of them were clearly our fault, and resulted from our crude
                    approach to URL construction. One site, the <title rend="italic">Robert Graves
                        Diary</title>, was represented by only a handful of static pages, since the
                    majority of its content was designed to be accessed through explicit searches
                    from the home page, with the search parameters encoded in URL query strings; the
                    crawler would have had no way to know what pages existed on the site other than
                    the few information and background pages linked directly from the home page. On
                    the live versions of these sites, any pages accessed by a user were typically
                    constructed on the fly by XQuery and XSLT, so they did not exist in any form
                    which could be backed up even locally by any normal method.</p>

                <p>Digging deeper into methods for backing up and replicating our projects within
                    our own institution revealed other problems. Some sites and applications
                    included hard-coded links to local resources using absolute URLs rather than
                    relative ones, so if the site were replicated in a different location, it would
                    still be dependent on, and prone to send the user over to, the original
                    site.</p>

                <p>Another problem faced by projects backed by online databases was a lack of
                    consistency in versioning of content. Typically, multiple project members had
                    rights to upload new material directly into the live database, thus
                        <q>publishing</q> it, but there was no attempt to ensure that the current
                    state of the live site was — in Endings parlance — coherent, consistent, and
                    complete (see <ptr target="#holmesTakeda2019b"/>). Someone editing a primary
                    source text might upload a new chapter to the site, forgetting that it contained
                    links to newly-added people in the personography or locations in the
                    placeography which also needed to be uploaded, so those links would fail. Every
                        <q>page</q> might have a different publication date, and the site overall
                    had no version or edition information, so anyone citing it would be forced to
                    fall back on the rather unfortunate <q>last accessed</q> date to anchor their
                    citation, knowing that the specific version of the document they were citing
                    might change tomorrow with no warning and no way to retrieve the previous
                    version. This was a problem of project organization rather than a technical
                    issue, and it arose largely out of the working methods emerging in the early
                    2000s. In the excitement provoked by the new affordances and publication
                    possibilities inherent in digital projects, there was a tendency to publish
                    anything and everything as quickly as possible. A measured and thoughtful
                    approach to <q>rolling publication</q> is of course possible, but, as we discuss
                    in section 5.5, our work on Endings has convinced us that for most projects, a
                    more traditional edition-based methodology is better.</p>

                <p>Finally, we were forced to acknowledge that few of our projects had adequate
                    documentation, making remediation and reconstruction doubly difficult.</p>

                <p>We had, it seemed, spent a dozen years enthusiastically generating fragile,
                    unmanageable, unmaintainable, unarchivable contraptions, and we were going to
                    pay the price for our thoughtlessness.</p>

                <p>This is not an unusual situation. In fact, our research suggests that it is the
                    norm for DH projects.<note>In our Endings survey, for example, 31% of projects
                        used a MySQL database, 15% used Drupal, and 18% used WordPress; others
                        depended on Ruby/Rails, Django, Omeka, Plone, Cocoon, and eXist.</note> Many
                    DH web applications are built rapidly, using off-the-shelf frameworks and
                    libraries which date quickly and are ultimately guaranteed to fail, and most
                    projects either rebuild their applications in repeated cycles of funding, or see
                    them languish and ultimately disappear. Our situation was perhaps more pointed
                    and critical because we are a base-funded unit with a long lifetime, committed
                    to maintaining our projects even after their initial funding is exhausted. Units
                    like ours are still relatively rare; in most cases, there is little or no
                    institutional help and no expectation of any. But having caused the problem, we
                    now had to fix it, not just by rebuilding multiple large projects, but by doing
                    so in such a way that we would not have to do the same work again in another ten
                    years.</p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>4. The Endings Project</head>

                <p>The Endings Project was set up as a formal collaboration between the HCMC
                    programmers grappling with the issue of project obsolescence, four Principal
                    Investigators leading some of our largest and longest-running active projects,
                    and a group from the University Library that specialized in digital preservation
                    and collections. We began with the aim of researching, formalizing, and testing
                    a range of strategies for rewriting four projects — <title rend="italic">The Map
                        of Early Modern London</title>, <title rend="italic">Le Mariage sous
                        L’Ancien Régime</title>, the <title rend="italic">Nxaʔamxcín Dictionary
                        Database</title>, and the <title rend="italic">Robert Graves Diary</title> —
                    with longevity in mind. The project, formally titled Endings: Concluding,
                    Archiving, and Preserving Digital Projects for Long-Term Usability, was funded
                    by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC) for
                    four years starting in April 2016. Since then, we have added many more projects,
                    some new and some dating back many years, to the project portfolio, and there
                    are now 14 projects under the Endings umbrella. Each individual project has
                    provided its own unique set of challenges and resulted in fresh ideas and
                    strategies as we have learned to build static sites from them.</p>

                <p>The Endings project has produced a range of outputs, including a survey with
                    follow-up interviews, software, many articles and presentations, many
                    static-site digital editions,<note>The Appendix lists most of the static sites
                        we have produced so far.</note> and the 2021 symposium from which this
                    special issue was born. But perhaps the most important outcome of our work has
                    been the set of principles that codifies our approach to site-building.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>5. Endings Principles, or: from Tamagotchis to Pet Rocks</head>

                <p>Readers of a certain age may remember the 1990s craze for the Tamagotchi, an
                    electronic device that was designed to mimic a pet animal by requiring regular
                    attention — feeding, education, play — from its owner in order to keep it
                    healthy. Our digital edition projects had become rather like Tamagotchis in
                    requiring constant tending simply to keep them functional. Slightly older
                    readers, however, may remember a similar, pre-digital fad from the 1980s. The
                    Pet Rock was exactly what it purported to be: a piece of rock, which required
                    nothing whatsoever from its owner. <quote rend="inline"
                        source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pet_Rock">A rock would not need to be
                        fed, walked, bathed, or groomed, and it would not die, become sick, or be
                        disobedient</quote> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pet_Rock"
                        >Wikipedia</ref>). Our Endings mission was to devise methods for turning our
                    Tamagotchis into Pet Rocks.</p>

                <p>The Endings Principles present a set of simple guidelines for this process, and
                    are intended for two audiences: researchers who have Tamagotchi projects that
                    are already too needy, and who are looking for an exit strategy; and (more
                    importantly) researchers in the early stages of planning and setting up new
                    projects, who are in a position to build a sustainable, low-maintenance digital
                    edition from the outset.</p>

                <p>This article lays out and discusses version 2.2 of the Endings Principles. This
                    version does not differ substantially from the initial draft, first published on
                    the Endings website in 2018, but the major sections have been re-ordered. Those
                    sections cover the five principal aspects of a digital edition project which we
                    consider to be crucial in designing for longevity: Data, Documentation,
                    Processing, Products, and Release Management.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>5.1 Data</head>

                    <p>Data is the expression of the source information, knowledge, and expertise of
                        our researchers, and forms the basis and <quote rend="inline">necessary
                            context for analytical claims</quote> (Thieberger in this issue, and
                            <ptr target="#thieberger2016"/>). Digital Humanities praxis has often
                        tended to blur the distinction between data and products; according to <ref
                            target="#baratsSchaferFickers2020">Barats, Schafer, and Fickers</ref>,
                        for example, <cit><quote rend="inline">data management is not just about the
                                data that are used, but also about those, which are produced
                                (metadata, results of research, etc.). In fact, data management
                                covers the whole life cycle of a research project, from data
                                selection to their curation and description, from analyse and
                                interpreting data to its publication and long term storage</quote>
                            <dhq:citRef><ref target="#baratsSchaferFickers2020">para
                                4</ref></dhq:citRef></cit>. For the purpose of Endings principles,
                        our definition of data is much more constrained: we define data as the
                        source material from which end-user products are generated. In the case of a
                        digital edition, data may take the form of TEI XML encodings of primary
                        source or born-digital documents, but it may also include relational
                        database data, digital images, audio or video recordings, and any other
                        material acquired or generated during research, but which does not form part
                        of the end product.</p>

                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.1 Data is stored only in formats which conform to open standards
                            and which are amenable to processing (TEI XML, GML, ODF, TXT).</head>

                        <p>It is now common practice for funding agencies and host institutions to
                            insist that projects create detailed data management plans. The Canadian
                            Tri-Agency Statement of Principles on Digital Data Management, for
                            example, specifies that <cit><quote rend="inline">data should be
                                    collected and stored throughout the research project using
                                    software and formats that ensure secure storage, and enable
                                    preservation of and access to the data well beyond the duration
                                    of the research project</quote>
                                <dhq:citRef><ptr target="#govCan2016"/></dhq:citRef></cit>. In
                            practice, this means using open, well-documented standards and file
                            formats (i.e. files that can be read, opened, and processed without the
                            need of special software or tools) instead of proprietary formats.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.2 Data is subject to version control (Subversion, Git).</head>

                        <p>The use of version control for DH data is now widely accepted practice;
                            by its very nature it supports LOCKSS (Lots of Copies Keep Stuff Safe)
                            (every person checking out the repository to work on it creates a new
                            copy), provides security against human error and data corruption, and
                            enables sophisticated progress tracking (<ptr target="#holmesEtAl2019"
                            />). We also believe that project history, as reflected in progressive
                            changes to its dataset, merits preservation in itself, and version
                            control systems support this. Jim McGrath, at our Endings Symposium,
                            discussed in detail the importance of recognizing and surfacing
                            contributions by students, post-doctoral researchers, and other
                                <q>precarious</q> labour, and Jessica Otis (in this issue) also
                            addresses this topic. Version control allows detailed tracking of
                            contributions file-by-file, allowing for more granular visualization of
                                responsibilities.<note>See, for example, this video of SVN commits
                                generated using Gource from MoEML’s svn repository: <ptr
                                    target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qor69c2Cvmc"
                            />.</note></p>
                    </div>

                    <div>

                        <head>5.1.3 Data is continually subject to validation and diagnostic
                            analysis.</head>

                        <p>Since all products depend entirely on the reliability of the project’s
                            dataset, it is essential to establish and maintain the accuracy of the
                            data. For XML datasets, all files should be validated against the
                            appropriate schemas; for other types of data, routines should be built
                            into processing that confirm that the project’s data conforms to the
                            project’s determined syntax and convention.<note>We discuss this
                                processing in greater detail in 5.4.</note> In addition to
                            confirming that individual files validate against the project’s schema,
                            the entire dataset should also be checked using a set of what we have
                            previously called <cit><quote rend="inline">diagnostics</quote>
                                <dhq:citRef><ptr target="#holmesTakeda2019b"/></dhq:citRef></cit>.
                            As we argued, projects contain multiple internal and external
                            relationships — to project-defined entities, other pages within the
                            project, or external vocabularies — that <cit><quote rend="inline">need
                                    to be tested, checked, and validated, too, but it is impractical
                                    to do this using document-level schemas</quote>
                                <dhq:citRef><ptr target="#holmesTakeda2019b" loc="i101–2"
                                    /></dhq:citRef></cit>. Taken together, standard document
                            validation and diagnostics are necessary for confirming that a project
                            is consistent, coherent, and complete.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>5.2 Documentation</head>

                    <p>Within the digital humanities (and many other fields), the literature of best
                        practices is suffused with exhortations to document more, document better,
                        and document everything. The reality for grant-funded projects, however, is
                        that documentation is frequently the last task on the agenda and therefore
                        likely to be curtailed or neglected when funding runs out or deadlines
                        approach (<ptr target="#morgan2021"/>). The Endings survey found that
                                <cit><quote rend="inline">60% [of projects] claimed to have a
                                clearly documented data model, but 90% of those that had
                                documentation considered it to be partial or inadequate, so it
                                appears that a project’s data model is well documented in only about
                                50% of cases</quote>
                            <dhq:citRef><ptr target="#arneilHolmesNewton2019"/></dhq:citRef></cit>.
                        We are no different in our exhortations to document thoroughly, but we do
                        take a strong position regarding the availability of documentation.</p>

                    <div>
                        <head>5.2.1 Data models, including field names, descriptions, and controlled
                            values, should be clearly described in a static document that is
                            maintained with the data and forms part of the products.</head>

                        <p>In most of our larger projects, such as <title rend="italic">The Map of
                                Early Modern London</title>, training for research assistants and
                            other contributors forms a core part of the project’s mission, and we
                            have learned to build this kind of praxis documentation directly into
                            the published digital edition itself. This has two significant
                            advantages over keeping documentation segregated and private. First,
                            since the documentation is published with the edition, it will always
                            travel with the published product, increasing the likelihood that future
                            researchers will be able to make sense of our materials and adopt or
                            repurpose them easily. Second, the visibility of our documentation helps
                            to keep us honest. Documentation is less prone to be aspirational and
                            more likely to reflect the reality of our praxis if users of our
                            editions can read it alongside the editions themselves, and point out
                            any failures or discrepancies.</p>

                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>5.2.2 All rights and intellectual property issues should be clearly
                            documented. Where possible the Data and Products should be released
                            under open licenses (Creative Commons, GNU, BSD, MPL).</head>

                        <p>As suggested above, a project’s best chance of long-term survival lies in
                            making it as amenable as possible to copying and repurposing. While this
                            article is mainly concerned with overcoming the technical barriers to
                            digital longevity, it must also be noted that any materials or data
                            accompanied by any sort of restrictive covenant or license will
                            inevitably be less appealing to a future researcher considering making
                            use of it. In the same way, the LOCKSS preservation strategy requires
                            the collaboration of multiple institutions willing to host project
                            products over the long term, and this is much less likely to happen if
                            licensing issues make it more difficult to deliver the materials to the
                            institution’s end-users in a convenient way. Therefore we strongly
                            recommend that projects, where possible, make all their materials
                            available under generous Creative Commons licenses, open-source all
                            their code, and avoid depending on any proprietary data, programming,
                            libraries, or other resources. For example, it is far better to try to
                            acquire your own copy of a historical text and scan the pages yourself
                            than to build a digital edition around page-images supplied under
                            license by a corporation or other rights-holder who may restrict access
                            to them.<note>There are of course contexts in which it may be impossible
                                to make all data publicly available; one of our own Endings
                                projects, the <title rend="italic">Nxa’amxcín Database and
                                    Dictionary</title>, contains culturally-sensitive personal and
                                linguistic data which cannot be shared outside the original language
                                community.</note></p>

                        <p>Even worse than restrictive licensing is lack of clarity about license
                            terms. If an institution or a researcher cannot discover the terms under
                            which content has been released, they will never be able to determine
                            whether they can or should archive or make use of it.</p>

                    </div>


                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>5.3 Processing</head>

                    <p>There is no unique way to create an Endings-compliant site; different
                        projects demand different technologies and there is no single language,
                        framework, or tool that will work for every case. So the principles below
                        are necessarily technology-agnostic and, while our own personal preferences
                        may become apparent from the examples, we do not advocate for one “stack”
                        over another. But there is certainly no shortage of processing pipelines for
                        creating static sites. The uptake of the <q>JAMstack</q> (Javascript, API,
                        and Markup) — a movement that grew out of the popularity of Node.js and NPM
                        and is now closely allied with static asset providers like GitHub, Netlify,
                        and Amazon S3 — has lead to both the popularization and proliferation of
                        static site generators, such as Next.js, Hugo, and Jekyll.<note>At the time
                            of writing, the JAMStack website lists 326 generators across 45
                            programming languages.</note> Within the digital humanities, proponents
                        of <q>minimal computing</q> have mobilized these tools to create frameworks
                        that significantly minimize the barriers to access in creating static
                        digital editions and digital exhibits.<note>Some of the most popular of
                            these tools are the GO:DH Minimal Computing Group’s digital-edition
                            platform <q>Ed</q> and their digital exhibit builder <q>Wax</q> as well
                            as LIB-Static’s <q>Collection Builder.</q> For a more comprehensive
                            outline of the goals of minimal computing for the GO:DH Minimal
                            Computing Group, see <ptr target="#gil2015"/> and <ptr
                                target="#sayers2016"/>. There is also a growing interest in the use
                            of static collections within libraries as demonstrated by <ptr
                                target="#newson2017"/>, <ptr target="#diaz2018"/>, and <ptr
                                target="#wikleWilliamsonBecker2020"/>.</note></p>

                    <p>But just because a pipeline produces static HTML output doesn’t mean that the
                        processing produces a site that is archivable and sustainable in the long
                        term. The Endings team was made painfully aware of this in the creation of
                        our own Endings website, which was built initially using GitHub Pages and a
                        pre-built Jekyll template. Though completely static, the site violated many
                        core Endings principles: it was comprised of malformed, invalid HTML that
                        relied on Bootstrap 4 and a set of JQuery-based JavaScript to handle various
                        UI components. The site has since been developed into valid XHTML5 with all
                        JQuery dependencies replaced by CSS3 and all updates handled by XSL
                        transformations managed by an Ant build script. The problem with the old
                        Endings site was not that it was built with Jekyll and that, had we just
                        used Ant and XSL in the first place, all of our problems would have been
                        solved; rather, the main issue was that the processing was meant only to
                        create a static site, and not one that was coherent, consistent, complete,
                        and free of technical debt.</p>

                    <p>We understand processing, then, not in terms of a particular pipeline, tool,
                        or programming language, but rather as the set of steps necessary for
                        creating robust, sustainable, and archivable resources. While we have
                        created some tools — like our diagnostics toolsets<note>See <ptr
                                target="https://github.com/projectEndings/diagnostics"/> and <ptr
                                target="https://github.com/projectEndings/html_diagnostics"
                            />.</note> as well as staticSearch, which is discussed in detail in
                        Section 6 — as part of the Endings project, these toolsets are neither
                        necessary nor sufficient for an Endings <q>processing</q> pipeline.</p>

                </div>


            </div>


        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>, and delete dummy record below. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->
                <bibl xml:id="arneilHolmes1998" label="Arneil and Holmes 1998"><name>Arneil,
                        S.</name>, and <name>Holmes, M. D</name>. 1998. <title rend="quotes">Hot
                        Potatoes: Free Tools for Creating Interactive Language Exercises for the
                        World Wide Web,</title> Paper presented at the EuroCALL conference, Leuven
                    (September 1998).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="arneilHolmes1999" label="Arneil and Holmes 1999"><name>Arneil,
                        S.</name>, and <name>Holmes, M. D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Juggling hot potatoes: Decisions and compromises in
                        creating authoring tools for the Web.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">ReCALL Journal</title> 11.2: 12-19 and College and
                    University Media Review, Vol. 6 No. 1. CUP; CCUMC (September 1999) <ptr
                        target="https://web.archive.org/web/20050526203034/http://www.eurocall-languages.org/recall/pdf/rvol11no2.pdf"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="arneilHolmes2001" label="Arneil and Holmes 2001"><name>Arneil,
                        S.</name>, and <name>Holmes, M. D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Hot Potatoes, History and Future,</title> Paper presented
                    at EuroCALL Conference, Nijmegen, August 2001. <ptr
                        target="https://web.uvic.ca/hrd/eurocall2001/HotPotPastFuture/PastFutureHome.htm"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="arneilHolmesNewton2019" label="Arneil, Holmes and Newton 2019"
                        ><name>Arneil, S.</name>, <name>Holmes, M. D.</name>, and <name>Newton,
                        G.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Project Endings: Early Impressions From Our Recent Survey
                        On Project Longevity In DH.</title> Paper presented by Greg Newton at
                    Digital Humanities 2019 Conference, Utrecht, the Netherlands, July 2019. <ptr
                        target="https://dev.clariah.nl/files/dh2019/boa/0891.html"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="baratsSchaferFickers2020" label="Barats, Schafer and Fickers 2020"
                        ><name>Barats, C.</name>, <name>Schafer, V.</name>, and <name>Fickers,
                        A.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Fading Away… The challenge of sustainability in digital
                        studies.</title> DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly, 14.3 (2020). <ptr
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/14/3/000484/000484.html"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="burnard2016" label="Burnard 2016"><name>Burnard, L.</name> 2016.
                        <title rend="quotes">How to Update Your ODD.</title> TEI GitHub Repository
                    (2016). <ptr target="http://teic.github.io/PDF/purifyDoc.pdf"/>. (accessed 18
                    February 2019).</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="cayless2010" label="Cayless 2010"><name>Cayless, H.</name> 2010.
                        <title rend="quotes">Ktêma es aiei: Digital Permanence from an Ancient
                        Perspective.</title> In Mahony, S., and Bodard, G. (eds), Digital Research
                    in the Study of Classical Antiquity, pp. 139-150. <ptr
                        target="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/chapters/edit/10.4324/9781315577210-18/kt%C3%AAma-es-aiei-digital-permanence-ancient-perspective-hugh-cayless"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="diaz2018" label="Diaz 2018"><name>Diaz, C.</name> 2018. <title
                        rend="quotes">Using static site generators for scholarly publications and
                        open educational resources.</title> The Code4Lib Journal, 42 (2018). <ptr
                        target="https://journal.code4lib.org/articles/13861"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="gelawEtAl2002" label="Gelaw et al. 2002"><name>Gelaw, D.</name>,
                        <name>Hastings, S.</name>, and <name>Hartman, C.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">A Metadata Approach to Preservation of Digital Resources:
                        The University of North Texas Libraries’ Experience.</title> First Monday
                    7.8 (2002). <ptr
                        target="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/981"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="gil2015" label="Gil 2015">Gil, A. <title rend="quotes">The User, the
                        Learner and the Machines We Make.</title> Minimal Computing: A Working Group
                    of GO::DH, 21 May 2015. <ptr
                        target="http://godh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2015/05/21/user-vs-learner/"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="goddardSeeman2019" label="Goddard and Seeman 2019"><name>Goddard,
                        L.</name>, and <name>Seeman, D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Chapter 3: Negotiating Sustainability: Building Digital
                        Humanities Projects that Last.</title> In <name>Crompton, C.</name>,
                        <name>Lane, R.J.</name>, and <name>Siemens, S.</name> (eds), <title
                        rend="italic">Doing More Digital Humanities</title> (2019). London:
                    Routledge.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="govCan2016" label="Government of Canada 2016"><name>Government of
                        Canada</name>. <title rend="italic">Tri-Agency Statement of Principles on
                        Digital Data Management</title> (2016, updated 2021). 2016 (updated 2021).
                        <ptr target="https://science.gc.ca/eic/site/063.nsf/eng/h_83F7624E.html"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmes1997" label="Holmes 1997"><name>Holmes, M. D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Web Language.</title> Online presentation showcasing the
                    use of JavaScript-based exercises for language teaching (1997). <ptr
                        target="https://web.uvic.ca/lancenrd/martin/weblang/"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmes2017a" label="Holmes 2017a"><name>Holmes, M. D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Whatever happened to interchange?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> (2017) 32
                    (suppl_1): i63-i68. Oxford University Press/EADH. <ptr
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw048"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmes2017b" label="Holmes 2017b"><name>Holmes, M. D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Selecting Technologies for Long-Term Survival.</title>
                    Paper presented at the SHARP Conference 2017: Technologies of the Book,
                    Victoria, BC, Canada, June 2017. <ptr
                        target="https://github.com/projectEndings/Endings/raw/master/presentations/SHARP_2017/mdh_sharp_2017.pdf"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmesEtAl2019" label="Holmes et al 2019"><name>Holmes, M. D.</name>,
                        <name>Fralick, K.</name>, <name>Fukushima, K.</name> and <name>Karlson,
                        S.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">How we tripled our encoding speed in the Digital Victorian
                        Periodical Poetry project.</title> Paper presented at the Text Encoding
                    Initiative Conference, Graz, Austria, September 2019. <ptr
                        target="https://zenodo.org/record/3449241"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmesTakeda2018" label="Holmes and Takeda 2018"><name>Holmes, M.
                        D.</name>, and <name>Takeda, J.</name> 2018. <title rend="quotes">Why do I
                        need Four Search Engines?</title> Proceedings of the Japanese Association of
                    Digital Humanities Conference, Tokyo, Japan (2018). <ptr
                        target="https://conf2018.jadh.org/files/Proceedings_JADH2018"
                    />.pdf#page=58</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmesTakeda2019a" label="Holmes and Takeda 2019a"><name>Holmes, M.
                        D.</name>, and <name>Takeda, J.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">The Prefabricated Website: Who needs a server
                        anyway?</title> Paper presented at the Text Encoding Initiative Conference,
                    Graz, Austria, September 2019. <ptr target="https://zenodo.org/record/3449197"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmesTakeda2019b" label="Holmes and Takeda 2019b"><name>Holmes, M.
                        D.</name> and <name>Takeda, J.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Beyond Validation: Using Programmed Diagnostics to Learn
                        About, Monitor, and Successfully Complete Your DH Project.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 34 (suppl_1)
                    (December 2019): i100–i109. Oxford University Press/EADH. <ptr
                        target="https://doi.org/10"/>.1093/llc/fqz011</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="holmesTakeda2020" label="Holmes and Takeda 2020"><name>Holmes, M.
                        D.</name> and <name>Takeda, J.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Static Search: An Archivable and Sustainable Search Engine
                        for the Digital Humanities.</title> Paper presented at the Digital
                    Humanities Summer Institute (DHSI) Colloquium (#VirtualDHSI), 6 June 2020. <ptr
                        target="https://zenodo.org/record/3883150"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="interpares2013" label="InterPARES 2013"><name>InterPARES 3 Team Canada
                        (International Research on Permanent Authentic Records in Electronic
                        Systems)</name>. Case Study 09: Alma Mater Society of The University of
                    British Columbia: Policies and Procedures for Web Site Preservation. May 2013.
                        <ptr
                        target="http://www.interpares.org/ip3/display_file.cfm?doc=ip3_canada_cs09_wks02_action_25_v1-3.pdf"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="jakobsenOrlandi2016" label="Jakobsen and Orlandi 2016"><name>Jakobsen,
                        J.</name>, and <name>Orlandi. C.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">On the CCA (in)security of MTProto.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">SPSM ’16: Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Security and
                        Privacy in Smartphones and Mobile Devices, October 2016</title>, 113–116.
                    New York: Association for Computing Machinery. <ptr
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2994459.2994468"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="molloy2011" label="Molloy 2011">Molloy, L. <title rend="quotes">Oh,
                        the Humanities! A Discussion about Research Data Management for the Arts and
                        Humanities Disciplines.</title> In: JISC MRD - <title rend="italic">Evidence
                        Gathering</title> 2011. <ptr target="http://mrdevidence.jiscinvolve"
                    />.org/wp/2011/12/16/oh-the-humanities-a-discussion-about-</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="morgan2021" label="Morgan 2021"><name>Morgan, P.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Further thoughts on collectivity.</title> Blog Post,
                    January 27, 2021. <ptr
                        target="http://blog.paigemorgan.net/articles/21/further-thoughts.html"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="morreale2019" label="Morreale 2019"><name>Morreale, L.</name> 2019.
                        <title rend="quotes">Medieval Digital Humanities and the Rite of Spring:
                        Thoughts on Performance and Preservation.</title> BodoArXiv. July 18.
                    doi:10.34055/osf.io/7p2t6.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="newson2017" label="Newson 2017"><name>Newson, K.</name> 2017. <title
                        rend="quotes">Tools and workflows for collaborating on static website
                        projects.</title> The Code4Lib Journal. (2017) 38. <ptr
                        target="https://journal.code4lib"/>.org/articles/12779</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="nielsenJakob1999" label="Jakob Nielsen 1999"><name>Nielsen,
                        Jakob</name>. <title rend="quotes">Graceful Degradation of Scalable Internet
                        Services.</title> Nielsen Norman Group Website, 1999. <ptr
                        target="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/graceful-degradation-of-scalable-internet-services/"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="nielsenJim2021" label="Jim Nielsen 2021"><name>Nielsen, Jim</name>.
                        <title rend="quotes">Web Languages as Compile Targets.</title> Jim Nielsen’s
                    Blog, 5 April 2021. <ptr
                        target="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2021/web-languages-as-compile-targets/"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="rinaldi2015" label="Rinaldi 2015"><name>Rinaldi, B.</name>
                    <title rend="italic">Static Site Generators.</title> O’Reilly Media Inc. 2015.
                        <ptr target="https://www.oreilly"/>.com/library/view/
                    static-site-generators/9781492048558/</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="saachi2015" label="Saachi 2015">Saachi, S.. <title rend="quotes">What
                        Do We Mean by ‘Preserving Digital Information’? Towards Sound Conceptual
                        Foundations for Digital Stewardship.</title> PhD thesis, University of
                    Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 2015. Columbia University Academic Commons. <ptr
                        target="https://academiccommons.columbia.edu/doi/10.7916/D8Z60WN2/download"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="sayers2016" label="Sayers 2016">Sayers, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Minimal Definitions.</title> Minimal Computing: A Working Group of GO::DH,
                    2 October 2016. <ptr
                        target="http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/02/minimaldefinitions/"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="takedaLines2019" label="Takeda and Lines 2019"><name>Takeda, J.</name>
                    and <name>Lines, S.</name> 2019. <title rend="quotes">Using Github and its
                        Integrations to Create, Test, and Deploy a Digital Edition,</title> Paper
                    presented at the Text Encoding Initiative conference, Graz, Austria (September
                    2019). <ptr target="https://gams.uni-graz.at/o:tei2019"/>.174</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="thieberger2016" label="Thieberger 2016"><name>Thieberger, N.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">What remains to be done – Exposing invisible collections in
                        the other 7000 languages and why it is a DH enterprise.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> 32(2) (2016),
                    1:423–434. <ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw006"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="unsworth1997" label="Unsworth 1997"><name>Unsworth, J.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Documenting the Reinvention of Text: The Importance of
                        Failure.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">The Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>, 3.2 (December
                    1997). doi:10.3998/3336451.0003.201.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="viglianti2017" label="Viglianti 2017"><name>Viglianti, R.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Your Own Shelley-Godwin Archive: An off-line strategy for
                        on-line publication.</title> Paper presented at the TEI Conference,
                    Victoria, BC, Canada, November 2017. <ptr
                        target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/tei2017/abstracts/t_126_viglianti_shelleygodwin.html"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="warwick2020" label="Warwick 2020"><name>Warwick, C.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">Interfaces, Ephemera, and Identity: A Study of the
                        Historical Presentation of Digital Humanities Resources.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 35.4
                    (December 2020): 944–971. <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqz081"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="wikleWilliamsonBecker2020" label="Wikle, Williamson, and Becker 2020"
                        ><name>Wikle, O.</name>, <name>Williamson, E.</name>, and <name>Becker,
                        D.</name>
                    <title rend="quotes">What is Static Web and What’s it Doing in the Digital
                        Humanities Classroom?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">dh+lib</title> 2020. <ptr
                        target="https://dhandlib.org/2020/06/22/what-is-static-web-and-whats-it-doing-in-the-digital-humanities-classroom/"
                    />.</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
