<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "balisage-1-5.dtd">-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="balisage-author.css" title="Authoring" alternate="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-html.xsl"?>
<article version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.5" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Balisage authoring stylesheets README</title>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>A quick README describing the stylesheets available for authors writing Balisage papers
        in XML, with <quote>how to</quote> instructions.</para>
    </abstract>
    <author>
<personname>
<firstname>Tonya</firstname>
<surname>Gaylord</surname>
</personname>
<personblurb><para>Tonya Gaylord has participated in Balisage since its inception in 2008, and in many other XML and markup industry conferences before and since.</para></personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Mulberry Technologies, Inc.</orgname>
      </affiliation></author></info>
<para>Three XSLT stylesheets are provided in this distribution for the convenience of Balisage authors
    writing conference papers, along with related materials:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem>
      <para><code>balisage-html.xsl</code> is a <quote>plain preview</quote> stylesheet generating a
        simple (HTML) web page suitable for printing. The CSS file <code>balisage-plain.css</code>
        is referenced by HTML generated by this stylesheet, and should be placed alongside these
        results.</para>
      <para>Initially used as a <quote>standalone</quote> stylesheet, <code>balisage-html.xsl</code> now calls in <code>theme.xsl</code> as an imported module and will not work unless both files are in the same subdirectory. (The <code>theme.xsl</code> stylesheet also includes Javascript instructions used to produce a full proceedings; any attempts to load Javascript while generating a single paper can be ignored.)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>balisage-proceedings-html.xsl</code> generates an HTML version of a paper in a form similar to its appearance in conference proceedings, with <quote>Proceedings look and
        feel</quote>. The CSS stylesheet <code>balisage-proceedings.css</code> should be used with
        its results.</para>
      <para>This stylesheet calls in <code>balisage-html.xsl</code> as an imported module, so that
        the logic used by both stylesheets is consistent. (Only the layout is different.) It will
        not work if <code>balisage-html.xsl</code> (and its imported module <code>theme.xsl</code>) are not also present in the same
        subdirectory.</para>
      <para>It will be a kindness to Balisage <emphasis role="ital">not</emphasis> to post on the
        Internet any HTML generated from these stylesheets. In order to avoid brand
        confusion, please use a variant you create for
        yourself.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>In addition, a CSS stylesheet <code>balisage-author.css</code> is provided, to apply
        directly to a Balisage XML paper, for use (for example) in structured editors. It is standard
        CSS and should work in a variety of tools, with minimal modification or tuning. (It has been
        tested in oXygen 22.1).</para>
      <para>This stylesheet calls in an additional CSS stylesheet, <code>docbook-table.css</code>,
        to handle table formatting. Even without this module, it should degrade gracefully (although tables will not be supported as fully).</para>
      <para>The <code>balisage-author.css</code> stylesheet affords styling for most Balisage structures and has been updated to include elements (such as those for accessibility) added by the Balisage 1.5 model.  Nonetheless, the preferred method to preview a Balisage paper is to generate an HTML version using the XSLT <code>balisage-proceedings-html.xsl</code> stylesheet described above.</para>  
    </listitem>    
</itemizedlist>
  <section>
    <title>How to use the XSLT</title>
    <section>
      <title>In a standalone processor</title>
      <para>The stylesheets use standard XSLT 3.0, so any conformant XSLT 3.0 processor can convert
        XML valid to the Balisage 1.5 DTD (or to RNG or XSD variants thereof) into HTML.
        Configuration will depend on your tool.</para>
      <para>After running a transformation and writing (serializing) the HTML results to a file, be
        sure that CSS stylesheets needed for the display are placed in the same
        subdirectory as the HTML file, and that any images called by the file are positioned
        correctly relative to it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>How to use the CSS</title>
    <para>To achieve formatted display in a structured XML editor such as oXygen, 
      use the <code>balisage-author.css</code> stylesheet provided here, binding it with a similar
      processing instruction at the top of your XML
      document:<programlisting xml:space="preserve">&lt;?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="balisage-author.css"?&gt;</programlisting></para>
    <para>Note that depending on your authoring environment&#8217;s support of CSS, you may have variable
      results. Consult your product documentation, or compare this CSS directly with CSS known to
      work in your tool, if you find adjustments need to be made.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>A mockup of a Balisage paper (<code>TagZoo.xml</code>) and its accompanying graphic files have been included in this distribution, along with HTML output generated using the Proceedings stylesheet (<code>balisage-proceedings-html.xsl</code>) in a structured XML editor such as oXygen.  In conjunction with the Balisage tag library, these two documents can assist authors tag and test their XML files to achieve the desired HTML display.</para>
    <para>This README document is an example of a valid Balisage paper with its stylesheets linked:
      open it in a browser and see (if you haven&#8217;t already). As distributed, it calls in the plain
      preview XSLT stylesheet (<code>balisage-html.xsl</code>) and the <code>balisage-author.css</code> CSS stylesheet.</para>
    <para>In both documents, the <code>DOCTYPE</code> declaration has been commented out to
      facilitate processing in uncontrolled environments; to validate either, correct and uncomment
      its declaration, or include another schema binding.</para>
  </section></article>
