<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information. Change the value of xml:lang if not English.-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Introduction to Special Issue: Project
                    Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo xml:id="martindholmes">
                    <dhq:author_name>Martin <dhq:family>Holmes</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3944-1116</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria Humanities Computing and Media
                        Centre</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mholmes@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Martin Holmes is a programmer in the University of Victoria Humanities
                            Computing and Media Centre. He is the lead programmer on several large
                            digital edition projects including the <title rend="italic">Map of Early
                                Modern London</title> (MoEML) and <title rend="italic">Le Mariage
                                sous l'Ancien Régime</title>, and is part of the Project Endings
                            team. He served on the TEI Technical Council from 2010 to 2015 and was
                            managing editor of the <title rend="italic">Journal of the Text Encoding
                                Initiative</title> from 2013 to 2015.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo xml:id="janellejenstad">
                    <dhq:author_name>Janelle <dhq:family>Jenstad</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1389-7921</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria Department of English</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jenstad@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Janelle Jenstad is Professor of English at the University of Victoria.
                            She directs <title rend="italic">The Map of Early Modern London</title>
                            (MoEML) and <title rend="italic">Linked Early Modern Drama
                                Online</title> (LEMDO), and co-coordinates the <title rend="italic"
                                >New Internet Shakespeare Editions</title> and <title rend="italic"
                                >Digital Renaissance Editions</title>. With Jennifer Roberts-Smith
                            and Mark Kaethler, she co-edited <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s
                                Language in Digital Media</title> (Routledge). Her essays and book
                            chapters have appeared in <title rend="italic">Shakespeare
                                Bulletin</title>, <title rend="italic">Elizabethan Theatre</title>,
                                <title rend="italic">EMLS</title>, <title rend="italic"
                                >JMEMS</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ</title>, <title
                                rend="italic">Digital Studies</title>, and other venues. For a full
                            list, see janellejenstad.com.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo xml:id="matthuculak">
                    <dhq:author_name>J. Matthew <dhq:family>Huculak</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2717-1112</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria Advanced Research Services &amp; Digital
                        Scholarship Librarian</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>huculak@uvic.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>J. Matthew Huculak is Head of Advanced Research Services at the
                            University of Victoria Libraries. He is the former director of the
                                <title rend="italic">Modernist Versions Project</title>, <title
                                rend="italic">OpenModernisms</title>, and managing editor of the
                                <title rend="italic">Modernism/modernity Print +</title> Platform,
                            winner of the Innovation in Publishing Award from the Association of
                            American Publishers. His research focuses on libraries, archives, print
                            history and modernist periodical production. For a list of his work,
                            visit lib.uvic.ca/huculakcv.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">[to be
                    assigned]<!-- including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110 --></idno>
                <idno type="volume">[to be
                    assigned]<!-- volume number, with leading zeroes: e.g. 006 --></idno>
                <idno type="issue">[to be
                    assigned]<!-- issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2 --></idno>
                <date>2022</date>
                <dhq:articleType>introduction</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!--         If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Encoded from original Google Doc by Martin Holmes, 2022-12.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>introduction, project resiliency, endings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>project resiliency</item>
                        <item>endings</item>
                        <item>introduction</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="#martindholmes" when="2022-12">Created the file and encoded the
                text.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <!-- DO WE NEED AN ABSTRACT FOR A SHORT INTRO? -->
                <p/>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>The end is where we start from.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Introduction to Special Issue: Project Resiliency in the Digital Humanities</head>
            <!-- Use <div> only if there is more than one section -->
            <div>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="block"> What we call the beginning is often the end<lb/> And to
                            make an end is to make a beginning. <lb/> The end is where we start
                            from. </quote>
                        <dhq:citRef>– T. S. Eliot, <title rend="quotes">Little
                            Gidding</title></dhq:citRef>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>
                    <quote rend="inline">The end is where we start from</quote>
                </head>

                <p>Over the past decade, digital humanists have come a long way in recognizing when
                    a project is <quote rend="inline">done</quote> (<ref target="#kirschenbaum2009"
                        >Kirschenbaum 2009</ref>). But DH still has a problem when it comes to
                    project resiliency. As Constance Crompton points out in her contribution to this
                    issue, DH grant funding is disproportionately awarded to new and shiny digital
                    technologies and tools rather than to disciplinary scholarship implemented and
                    published with standard digital tools. Almost no funding is available for
                    maintenance, remediation, upgrading, and remaking, even though technological
                    frameworks will have changed considerably in a five-year funding cycle. The
                    result is a huge maintenance burden for project leads and developers (Holmes
                    &amp; Takeda in this issue) and/or a hosting and storage problem for
                    institutions (Cummings in this issue). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><quote rend="inline">What we call a beginning</quote>: Project Endings</head>
                <p>Most of the papers in this DHQ special issue are the product of a virtual
                    symposium held in April 2021 by <ref target="https://endings.uvic.ca">The
                        Endings Project</ref> at the University of Victoria. The Endings Project, a
                    five-year collaboration funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research
                    Council (<ref target="http://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/">SSHRC</ref>), is creating
                    tools, principles, policies, code, and recommendations for digital scholarship
                    practitioners to create accessible, stable, long-lasting resources in the
                    humanities. Unusually for DH, the Endings Project was initiated by developers
                    (see Holmes &amp; Takeda in this issue). It brings together digital humanists
                    and librarians because, as Matthew Kirschenbaum has argued, <cit><quote
                            rend="inline">Digital humanists need the long-term perspective on data
                            that archivists have</quote>
                        <dhq:citRef><ptr target="#kirschenbaum2013"/></dhq:citRef></cit>. The
                    Endings team’s HCMC developers (all of them humanists by their first training)
                    are the bridge between Humanities researchers and Librarians/archivists,
                    facilitating a long-term conversation between the three constituencies
                    responsible for the intellectual generation, building, and long-term
                    preservation of digital research products. </p>

                <p>The impetus for The Endings Project was the substantial maintenance burden
                    accrued by UVic’s Humanities Computing and Media Centre (<ref
                        target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/">HCMC</ref>), which has been involved in over
                    200 digital humanities projects since the 1990s. Its history, as described in
                    Holmes &amp; Takeda, clearly shows the problems inherent in current approaches
                    to digital edition projects, particularly projects with short-term or sporadic
                    grant funding. The growing maintenance burden facing the HCMC was ultimately
                    unsustainable, and Project Endings was conceived and convened to address this
                    problem. </p>

                <p>The mission of The Endings Project was: <list type="unordered">
                        <item>to discover what human and institutional factors prevent completion of
                            projects;</item>
                        <item>to learn how to make web-based digital editions that will last
                            indefinitely without maintenance; and</item>
                        <item>to learn how to archive finished projects without placing undue
                            burdens on the repository.</item>
                    </list> Ultimately, we wanted to know how projects end, why and when they fail
                    to achieve their final milestone, what constitutes a good ending, and where best
                    to store the finished product so that its research outputs continue to be
                    available long-term. </p>


            </div>
            <div>
                <head><quote rend="inline">To evaporate one’s thoughts in a sonnet</quote>: Cultures
                    of constraint</head>

                <p>The Earl of Essex was said to have put his arguments to Queen Elizabeth in sonnet
                    form (<dhq:citRef><ptr target="#wotton1672" loc="165"/></dhq:citRef>). While
                    sonnets did not save the earl’s neck, we do believe that the answer to the
                    question of how to create long-term, accessible resources is found in
                    cultivating cultures of constraint. We have phrases like <quote rend="inline"
                        >scope creep</quote> and <quote rend="inline">feature creep</quote> to
                    describe the near-irresistible temptations to act on every good idea a project
                    member may have, but we may also introduce the term <quote rend="inline"
                        >platform creep</quote> to describe easy-to-deploy platforms that facilitate
                    rapid deployment of a new project, but incur technical debt leading to
                    inevitable obsolescence. Project leads, at the end of these types of projects,
                    are often surprised when their institutional library or archive is unable to
                    preserve the bespoke software stack they’ve cobbled together. Instead of trying
                    to preserve what we accidentally made, we should be trying to make what can be
                    preserved. </p>

                <p>The fewer flourishes in software, the longer the project seems to last. The
                    recent work of the HCMC has been to be innovative within a limited set of
                    technologies, in order to minimize the maintenance burden of over 200 projects,
                    so that developer time can be invested in newer projects coming in. We learned
                    quickly that a <q>simple</q> security update could render sites unreadable
                    necessitating constant tending and time. The need for action within very strict
                    constraints (time and funding) forced us to be creative to serve our users. </p>

                <p>There are unspoken constraints in the library, as well. Space and human resources
                    force librarians and archivists to make hard decisions on what stays and what
                    goes – weeding the stacks of unused material to make room for new books is one
                    of the less understood aspects of librarians’ jobs. Recently, a member of the
                    Humanist List-Serv asked why librarians can’t preserve digital projects as they
                    do books. It seems like a reasonable request at first glance, but when one
                    considers the vast number of bespoke DH projects that will require continual
                    software updates and rewrites in order to keep running, it quickly becomes an
                    unmanageable task — even with strong documentation created by the project (and
                    good documentation also tends to be something we run out of time to do).
                    Although libraries and archives can’t fire up hundreds or thousands of Wordpress
                    and Drupal sites, they can, certainly, run a server on which flat sites can be
                    stored, accessed, and preserved. That is not a problem. In this way, limitations
                    need to be the drivers of innovation and the DH community should see
                        <q>constraint</q> as an admirable feature of a project since it will give
                    the project the best chance of survival. As a community, we need to adopt
                    constraint as an aesthetic, and make it a part of <quote rend="inline">the
                        stories we tell,</quote> a phrase Claire Battershill explores in this issue,
                    about our work. </p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The Symposium</head>

                <p>The work of Endings began with a day seminar in which the UVic Endings
                    researchers, developers, and librarians<note>The Endings Team originally
                        consisted of researchers Claire Carlin, Ewa Czaykowska-Higgins, Elizabeth
                        Grove-White, and Janelle Jenstad; developers Stewart Arneil, Martin Holmes,
                        and Greg Newton; and librarians Corey Davis, John Durno, and Lisa Goddard.
                        Since 2016, Elizabeth Grove-White has retired, and J. Matthew Huculak has
                        replaced Corey Davis on the team. Research assistants and collaborators have
                        included Emily Comeau, Tye Landels, Daniel Martin, and Joey Takeda.</note>
                    met to describe their work, share their institutional vantage point, and learn
                    from each other. We made many surprising discoveries about each other and
                    deconstructed erroneous assumptions about the roles of our institutional
                    colleagues. For example, the Library’s position on archiving was effectively
                    invisible to researchers and developers; the web subdomain of a project
                    (mapoflondon.uvic.ca, for example) seemed self-evidently crucial to researchers
                    as an extension of the project’s title and <q>brand,</q> while to the Library it
                    seemed obvious that the subdomain didn’t matter at all and that an archived
                    project should be delivered through a library-specific domain. </p>

                <p>This day seminar led to our conducting a survey of DH practitioners, in order to
                    learn about the experiences and realities faced by those working in other
                    contexts and institutions. What we learned from the survey (see <ptr
                        target="#carlin2018"/>; <ptr target="#endingsTeam2022"/>) was not
                    surprising: most projects faced exactly the same sorts of problems and
                    limitations, although the scale of technical support and resources provided by
                    host institutions varied widely. From the 125 survey respondents, we identified
                    25 project leads with whom we conducted more in-depth interviews during 2019 and
                    2020. </p>

                <p>These interviews were then transcribed and encoded (see Comeau in this issue for
                    a detailed description of the interview and analysis process) to provide us with
                    a searchable resource from which we could easily draw examples and examine
                    general tendencies and issues across the DH landscape. Papers are forthcoming
                    that describe the results of those interviews. Finally, we invited a selection
                    of our interviewees from a range of different disciplines to continue the
                    co-created conversation by participating in the 2021 symposium that gave rise to
                    this special issue. </p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The Papers</head>

                <p>We begin with a pair of papers that address two of the key problems in foreseeing
                    an ending to a digital project. In <quote rend="inline">The Stories We
                        Tell,</quote> Claire Battershill addresses our very human reluctance to
                    imagine our own projects coming to an end. She proposes that if we think about
                    DH projects <quote rend="inline">in a literary sense, we can analyze and read
                        digital projects as the creative and multifaceted texts that they are and
                        become. We can perhaps approach them with intention and care not only as
                        technical artifacts but also as works that we’ve made, often along with a
                        number of collaborators.</quote> Projects begin in <quote rend="inline"
                        >promise, potential, and excitement</quote>; despite challenges along the
                    way, we keep projects going because the project becomes intrinsic to our purpose
                    and definition, especially for the many digital humanists in precarious
                    employment. Resolving disciplinary and other inequities would go a long way
                    towards helping projects reach their end, she argues, because a team in stable
                    institutional positions may keep collaborating on other projects, large or
                    small. Constance Crompton points out the ways in which funding structures that
                    reward innovation have discouraged sustainable, replicable practices until the
                        <quote rend="inline">recent turn to sustainability, signalled by the rise of
                        data management plans and data deposit requirements.</quote> Given the
                    self-replicating nature of DH practices through the apprenticeship model whereby
                    students work on large projects, mentorship will be a crucial factor in breaking
                    the cycle of unsustainable, boutique project building. </p>

                <p>James Cummings discusses two well-known digital edition projects, the <title
                        rend="italic">CURSUS</title> project and <title rend="italic">William
                        Godwin’s Diary</title>. Both projects were severely endangered by the lack
                    of legacy planning. When key personnel are lost, and a project has no champion
                    at its host institution, the consequences can be disastrous, especially when the
                    project depends on a technical framework which is not part of the institution’s
                    core infrastructure. Both of these projects would have been completely lost
                    without Cummings’s persistent intervention.</p>

                <p>In telling two digital disaster stories, Sara Diamond reminds us that even the
                    most important and socially significant projects are subject to institutional
                    changes, career moves, and shifting priorities. The Banff New Media Institute
                    was deaccessioned after a leadership change, resulting in the overnight
                    disappearance of a vast archive of Indigenous art and history. The Daniel
                    Langlois Foundation archive survived only because of the determined efforts of
                    Jean Gagnon, on whose good will the project is still worryingly dependent.
                    Diamond’s own fonds and sub-collections have been built with the lessons of
                    these two experiences in mind. Ultimately, Diamond suggests that <quote
                        rend="inline">institutions, creators of archives and their users all bear
                        responsibility for the protection and continuity</quote> of those
                    archives.</p>

                <p>Nick Thieberger’s paper, on the monumental PARADISEC project, describes an
                    attempt to thwart the forces of entropy on a massive scale. PARADISEC has
                    rescued over 14,000 hours of field audio tape recordings representing over 1200
                    languages from the Pacific Region, and is hosting them in a public archive, as
                    well as attempting to return them in accessible format to the originating
                    Indigenous communities. This enormous project is itself facing resiliency
                    issues, since it has no stable funding and depends on a small team of dedicated
                    researchers, reminding us that the process of data rescue and retrieval may be
                    cyclical and repetitive without reliable commitments to long-term archiving. </p>

                <p>Like Battershill, Jessica Otis is concerned with deconstructing narratives — in
                    this case the funding narratives that suggest, erroneously, that DH projects are
                    either <quote rend="inline">cash cows</quote> bringing money into the
                    institution via grants or <quote rend="inline">free</quote> because of donated
                    scholarly labor. Having shown the hidden costs of project maintenance, Otis
                    discusses the prospects of obtaining long-term funding to sustain a project
                    beyond its initial grant-funding, the availability of hard-funded resources from
                    the institution, and the practical realism required to retool projects to fit
                    into sustainable long-term funding models. </p>

                <p>There is a traditional assumption that what matters about a digital project is
                    its <q>data</q> (however we might define that), rather than its web interface,
                    which is considered ephemeral. However, every session at the symposium touched
                    on the issue of interface, arguably the most recognizable and least preservable
                    part of a digital project. Preserving the look and feel of web-based digital
                    projects continues to be a challenge. Symposium attendees discussed the
                    possibility of doing video captures of website tours and archiving video along
                    with a digital project’s data. Diamond points to emulation as a preservation
                    strategy, and we can undoubtedly learn much from the work of electronic
                    literature scholars as well. Emulation is expensive in terms of hardware,
                    software, and maintenance, and perhaps only works like those described by
                    Diamond will merit such preservation. </p>

                <p>Our final two papers were not presented at the symposium. However, Holmes and
                    Takeda, as Endings team members and co-hosts of the symposium, shared their
                    ideas in the discussion. They approach the practical issues of project
                    resiliency from a technical point of view. Their role on the Endings team was to
                    develop the detailed guidelines and recommended practices that would govern the
                    rewriting of many HCMC projects as pure static websites, and then to put the
                    guidelines into practice, rebuilding a dozen or so existing HCMC projects in
                    Endings-compliant form. Along the way, they developed diagnostic tools and an
                    entirely static search engine that can be deployed for any static digital
                    edition. </p>

                <p>Coble and Karlin’s paper is a serendipitous addition to our collection; the
                    authors were not presenters at our symposium, but their paper is an apt
                    counterpoint to the other work on project resiliency. They examine not the
                    reliability of individual project data and outputs, but the larger web of
                    scholarly referencing within which they live. Their research looks at citations
                    of digital resources from articles in <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> itself,
                    to see not just whether links still function, but also whether the resources to
                    which they point are the same resources the author intended to cite. </p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>

                <p>Sometimes things are meant to be ephemeral: there is ephemeral employment and
                    there are ephemeral products of scholarship, which is fine as long as
                    ephemerality is intentional. Yet the majority of DH projects find themselves in
                    the unfortunate position of being unintentionally ephemeral. One of the
                    anonymous reviewers of this issue made the point that we shouldn’t have to keep
                    making the point that digital projects need to be more robust and preservable.
                    The reviewer wondered why we are still having to advocate for what they
                    characterized as common knowledge and common sense. Taken together, the essays
                    in this collection show the difficulty of realizing common sense in practice.
                    The roots of this persistent problem are both social and technological. </p>

                <p>DH has a strong tradition of <q>collaboration,</q> which frequently includes
                    students, colleagues from across campus, and programmers, as well as librarians
                    and archivists. However, each group brings to the table its own cultural norms
                    and presuppositions, and each group works within existing structures of power,
                    funding, and promotion that are frequently at odds with one another.</p>

                <p>A faculty member who may want to launch a project quickly may be seduced by the
                    siren song of <q>easy to deploy,</q> which is nearly always at odds with
                    long-term survivability. A hastily-concocted Wordpress or Drupal site, although
                    ready for a promotion file — or replaced with the next big project — will be at
                    the mercy of how much time the scholar actually has to commit to regular updates
                    (usual answer: little to none). The programmer may resist the upfront work of
                    setting up a sustainable long-term platform because they are accustomed to
                    working with specific platform stacks and are tempted to fall back on what they
                    already know, or to pick up whatever library or platform is momentarily newest
                    and most interesting; projects built out of such a mindset will be at the mercy
                    of security vulnerabilities, software obsolescence, and personnel changes.
                    Librarians and archivists are constrained by a scarcity economy of space and
                    funding–it is easy to eschew preserving digital projects when you know it will
                    be impossible to maintain them. Although the dream of a <q>universal library</q>
                    is a beautiful ideal, it will nonetheless remain a fiction until we choose
                    universal technologies.</p>

                <p>The first stage in building an Endings-compliant project is having an honest
                    conversation among faculty, programmers, and librarians/archivists about
                    expectations, abilities, and sustainability that is agreed upon and documented.
                    This step should happen before the first byte is saved to disk. Normally trained
                    to work in solitude, faculty may need to rely on experts beyond their discipline
                    who work at a different pace. Programmers may have to be open to different ways
                    of programming and take the extra time to design for the eventual flattening of
                    sites even if a dynamic site is preferred for the length of the project (which
                    is perfectly fine, assuming there is funding and time for a complete rewrite at
                    the end). Librarians and archivists need to invest in people, services, and
                    technologies to sustain flat websites — which could simply be a server that is
                    part of the libraries’ long-term preservation plan. As this issue was being
                    created, the <title rend="italic"><ref target="https://graves.uvic.ca">Diary of
                            Robert Graves</ref></title> project became the first archived DH project
                    at UVic Libraries, a process which was possible only because the site is Endings
                    compliant. UVic Libraries is committing to preserving flattened,
                    Endings-compliant sites as part of its preservation activities. It has taken
                    some time to reach this point and the process has involved stakeholders from
                    across the institution (Systems, Metadata, Digital Scholarship, and the
                    University Librarian's Office), but we’re here. Hosting a server for static
                    sites is eminently achievable for most university libraries. With collaboration
                    comes compromise in the name of long-term access and discoverability. Everyone
                    on the team needs to understand the needs and limitations of the others, while
                    also mutually agreeing to Endings Principles. </p>

                <p>Finally, if there’s one constant in DH, and computing in general, it is that
                    technologies will change. Our toolkit is not merely a technological solution
                    that will be out of date next year. It is a series of practices for you to
                    consider when starting your project. Moreover, each DH project exists within a
                    unique environment with unique challenges. We’ve thus made our recommendations
                    adaptable to any project, at any scale, with the hope of creating something
                    sustainable. Who knows what tomorrow will bring? What we do know is that the
                    fewer dependencies a digital edition has, the longer it is likely to last. The
                    first HTML page marked up by Tim Berners-Lee in 1991 is still renderable by
                    modern browsers.<note><ptr
                            target="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/TheProject.html"/>.</note>
                    Simplicity for the win.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <!-- Encode each bibliographic item as <bibl>, and delete dummy record below. @xml:id and @label are required. All values for @xml:id should be lower-case. -->
                <bibl xml:id="carlin2018" label="Carlin 2018">Carlin, C. 2018. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Endings: Concluding, Archiving, and Preserving, Digital Projects for
                        Long-Term Usability.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                        Studies</title>, 2(1), p.19. DOI: <ptr
                        target="https://doi.org/10.5334/kula.35"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="endingsTeam2022" label="Endings Team 2022">Endings Team. 2022. <title
                        rend="quotes">Endings Project Survey Results.</title>
                    <ptr target="https://endings.uvic.ca/survey.html"/>.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2009" label="Kirschenbaum 2009">Kirschenbaum, Matthew G.
                    2009. <title rend="quotes">Done: Finishing Projects in the Digital
                        Humanities.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title> Volume 3
                    Number 2. <ptr
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000037/000037.html"
                    />.</bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum2013" label="Kirschenbaum 2013">Kirschenbaum, Matthew.
                    2013. <title rend="quotes">The .txtual Condition: Digital Humanities,
                        Born-Digital Archives and the Future Literary.</title> Digital Scholarship
                    in the Humanities Volume 7 Number 1. <ptr
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000151/000151.html"/>. </bibl>

                <bibl xml:id="wotton1672" label="Wotton 1672">Wotton, Sir Henry. <title
                        rend="italic">Reliquiae Wottonianae: Or, a Collection of Lives, Letters,
                        Poems, with Characters of Sundry Personages, and Other Incomparable Pieces
                        of Language and Art</title>. London: T. Roycroft, 1672.</bibl>


            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
