<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Prefabricated Website: Who Needs a Server Anyway?</title>
            <!-- author information in separate <author> elements per author -->
            <author>
               <name xml:id="mholmes">
                  <forename>Martin</forename>
                  <surname>Holmes</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><roleName>Programmer/Consultant</roleName>, <orgName>University of
                     Victoria Humanities Computing and Media Centre</orgName></affiliation>
               <email>mholmes@uvic.ca</email>
            </author>
            <author xml:id="jtakeda">
               <name>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname>Takeda</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation><roleName>MA Student</roleName>, <orgName>University of British Columbia
                  </orgName></affiliation>
               <email>joey.takeda@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date>2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>OpenEdition Journals -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for
               journals in the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking
               to publish full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <!-- a list of keywords, each in its own <term> -->
               <term>TEI and beyond: interactions, interchange, integrations and
                  interoperability</term>
               <term>TEI environments and infrastructures</term>
               <term>TEI and publication</term>
               <term>TEI and sustainability</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#jtakeda" when="2019-07-04">Copy edited the submission.</change>
         <change who="#mholmes" when="2019-06-28">Encoded the submission.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p><title level="m"><ref target="https://github.com/projectEndings">Project
                     Endings</ref></title>, a collaboration between digital humanists and
               librarians, is devising principles (<ref
                  target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/projectEndings/Endings/master/principles.txt"
                  >https://raw.githubusercontent.com/projectEndings/Endings/master/principles.txt</ref>)
               for building DH projects in ways that ensure that they remain viable, functional, and
               archivable into the distant future. Endings principles cover five components of
               project design: 
               
               <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>Data</item>
                  <item>Products</item>
                  <item>Processing</item>
                  <item>Documentation</item>
                  <item>Release Management</item>

               </list> Previous <title level="m">Endings</title> work has focused on Data and
               Products (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_2017a">Holmes 2017</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#arneil_holmes_2017">Arneil &amp; Holmes 2017</ref>) and diagnostic tools
               for monitoring project progress (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2018">Holmes
                  &amp; Takeda 2018</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2019"
                  >2019</ref>). This presentation will deal with the mechanics of Processing,
               focusing in particular on building large static sites which are resilient because
               they have no requirement for server-side technology at all. We will use the <title level="m"><ref
                  target="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/">Map of Early Modern London</ref></title> (MoEML) project as a case study.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <!-- text divisions, each with an @xml:id and <head> -->
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>

            <p><title level="m"><ref target="https://github.com/projectEndings">Project
                     Endings</ref></title>, a collaboration between digital humanists and
               librarians, is devising principles (<ref
                  target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/projectEndings/Endings/master/principles.txt"
                  >https://raw.githubusercontent.com/projectEndings/Endings/master/principles.txt</ref>)
               for building DH projects in ways that ensure that they remain viable, functional, and
               archivable into the distant future. Endings principles cover five components of
               project design: <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>Data</item>
                  <item>Products</item>
                  <item>Processing</item>
                  <item>Documentation</item>
                  <item>Release Management</item>

               </list> Previous <title level="m">Endings</title> work has focused on Data and
               Products (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_2017a">Holmes 2017</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#arneil_holmes_2017">Arneil &amp; Holmes 2017</ref>) and diagnostic tools
               for monitoring project progress (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2018">Holmes
                  &amp; Takeda 2018</ref> and <ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2019"
                  >2019</ref>). This presentation will deal with the mechanics of Processing,
               focusing in particular on building large static sites which are resilient because
               they have no requirement for server-side technology at all.</p>



            <p>We will use the <title level="m"><ref target="http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca">Map of
                     Early Modern London</ref></title> project (MoEML), one of the flagship Endings
               project, as a case study. Comprised of 2,000 TEI source files and 15,000 distinct
               entities, MoEML is a densely interlinked project that requires a sophisticated build
               process to create its website structure, the historical Agas Map interface, editions
               of primary source documents, various indexes and gazetteers, and encyclopedia
               entries. As a flagship Endings project, MoEML has been a testbed for the scalability
               of the Endings principles. The MoEML site has 9,000 HTML files, 26,000 XML files, and
               over 5,000 images, and is around 2GB in size. Our presentation will cover a number of
               key techniques in the build process, including: <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>Validation, validation, validation: XML, HTML, CSS, and TEI <gi>egXML</gi> example
                     code is validated at every stage of the build process. </item>
                  <item>Diagnostics to check all links and targets. </item>
                  <item>Unique query-free URLs for all entities </item>
                  <item>Generating the gazetteer, which includes every variant spelling of every
                     placename. </item>
                  <item>Pre-generating HTML fragments for AJAX retrieval for every entity.</item>
                  <item>Processing and rationalizing <gi>rendition</gi> elements and <att>style</att>
                     attributes. </item>
                  <item>Using document type taxonomies to build sitemaps and breadcrumb trails. </item>
                  <item>Filtering of images to include only those actually used.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="why">
            <head>Why build a static site?</head>
            <p>When in early 2019 the server which was hosting the tei-c.org website died, the
                  <title level="m">WordPress</title>-based main site disappeared from the Internet
               for a considerable time. Since <title level="m">WordPress</title> is a
               database-dependent system, a single central database host is required to run it, and
               until a new server could be brought up hosting that database, the site remained
               unavailable. However, there was no such problem with the TEI Guidelines, which are
               statically-built and available in multiple locations as a matter of course.<note>One
                  of the perspectives Holmes brought to the <title level="m">Endings</title> project
                  was his familiarity with the static build process for the TEI Guidelines, for
                  which we are primarily indebted to the late Sebastian Rahtz, a wise and clever man
                  who realized all this a long time ago.</note> A static site, however, can be replicated
               endlessly. All digital humanities projects will eventually end (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#kirschenbaum_2009">Kirschenbaum 2009</ref>; <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#rockwell_et_al_2014">Rockwell et al 2014</ref>), and their products will
               transition into minimally-curated archival hosting; static sites have much more
               chance of survival, availability and replication if they have no server dependencies. </p>

            <p>The world of large-scale software development is also coming to similar conclusions
               for slightly different reasons. The JamStack initiative (<ref xml:id="quoteref1"
                  type="bibl" target="#jamstack">JamStack.org</ref>) is also championing <quote
                  source="#quoteref1">modern web development architecture based on client-side
                  JavaScript, reusable APIs, and prebuilt Markup,</quote> in the interests of <quote
                  source="#quoteref1">better performance</quote>, <quote source="#quoteref1"
                  >cheaper, easier scaling</quote>, <quote source="#quoteref1">higher
                  security</quote>, and a <quote source="#quoteref1">better developer
                  experience</quote>. Long-term archivability is not a primary goal of JamStack;
               instead, one of their motivations is that a static site is far more easily deployed
               across Content Delivery Networks such as Akamai because it has no reliance on
               centralized back-end data sources such as a databases. Like JamStack, <title
                  level="m">Endings</title> advocates products based on pure client-side HTML5, CSS,
               and JavaScript. </p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="buildProcess">
            <head>The build process</head>

            <p><title level="m">MoEML</title>’s static build process, which is managed by <title
                  level="m">Apache Ant</title>, takes the densely-encoded, tightly-linked XML collection
               created by our team and builds from it a massive, loosely-coupled collection of web
               resources comprising everything we can possibly imagine an end-user might want to
               see. Before we start, though, we first check whether the current state of the
               collection is worth building into anything at all. We validate (RELAX NG), we validate
               again (Schematron), and we check coherence (does every link point to something
               meaningful?), consistency (does everything conform to the encoding guidelines and the
               editorial guidelines?), and completeness (does everything mentioned actually exist?)
               via our diagnostic processes (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2019">Holmes
                  &amp; Takeda 2019</ref>). If a single file is invalid, or a single link is broken,
               or an id is used for two different entities, the build fails and the process stops. A
               website with errors is not worth building.</p>

            <p>It is worth contrasting this rigorous suite of validation processes with the
                  pre-<title level="m">Endings</title> form of the <title level="m">MoEML</title>
               website, which was based on an <title level="m">eXist</title> XML database and to
               which project staff uploaded new and changed materials as they finished them (or
               thought they had finished them), when it occurred to them, or (sometimes)
               accidentally, while uploading other materials. Articles were
                  <soCalled>published</soCalled> containing links to other articles not yet written,
               or person records not yet added to the personography. One encoder would add an item to
               the bibliography with a new id, while another happened to use the same id for a
               location; both documents would be uploaded, and, at best, links would break and, at worst, the
               processing would fail to handle the error and break the site. Such issues were not
               rampant, but they were omnipresent. We will have no more of that.</p>

            <p>It should also be noted that these sorts of errors were not only caused by encoders;
               developers of the <title level="m">MoEML</title> site had to be very careful that any
               code committed to the eXist server was error-free. Testing code changes required a
               parallel hosting environment, which was an additional burden to maintain, and
               to keep synchronized with the live site. But by checking the validity of our outputs
               in the static build, we also necessarily ensure that our processes work: if
               everything in the build is valid, then, at the very least, the code itself can be
               compiled and it produces valid documents. Of course, this does not ensure that the
               code functions precisely the way we want it to, but, as we discuss later, the static
               build process gives the project time to ensure that the processes work as
               expected.</p>

            <p>Assuming all the validation tests pass, the first stage in building the website is to
               make more TEI XML. Lots of it, in fact. We build five different versions of our XML
               collection (see <ptr type="crossref" target="#fig_01"/>). <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#holmes_2017b">Holmes (2017b)</ref> provides a full description of the
               rationale behind this process, but the main justification is that we want to ensure
               that any future user who comes to our project looking for an XML document can likely
               find one that is tuned as closely as possible to their needs. We provide XML designed
               to best represent the praxis of our own project (<soCalled>original</soCalled> XML),
               XML designed to be less esoteric and that aligns more with standard TEI practices
                  (<soCalled>standard</soCalled> XML), XML designed to be most amenable to generic
               external processors (TEI Lite, TEI simplePrint), and XML designed to be detached
               entirely from the rest of the collection, free of external links and dependencies
                  (<soCalled>standalone</soCalled> XML). This is how we end up with 26,000 XML
               files, from a starting collection of only 2,000. As soon as each new version of the
               XML is created, you may easily guess what we do with it. We validate it. If any file
               fails validation, the build stops. 
               This is also when we create a wealth of new files that did not exist
               before, including the project gazetteer and a range of compiled indexes and similar
               materials whose information is inherent to the original XML, but which can now be
               made explicit and tangible. More of this in the next section.</p>

            <p>Finally, we begin to generate web products. A number of core principles govern the
               structure and organization of those products: <list rend="ordered">
                  <item><emph>Every entity</emph> (location, person, bibliography entry,
                     organization, article, etc.) has a <emph>unique id</emph>, and <emph>every
                        unique id gets its own individual page</emph> on the site. </item>

                  <item><emph>No URL is ever abandoned.</emph> If an id is changed or an entity is
                     removed from the collection, a page is still generated, redirecting to the new
                     version of the id, or to an explanation of what has happened. Linked Open Data
                     requires stable identifiers, so we have a responsibility to maintain them
                     indefinitely.</item>

                  <item><emph>Every page stands alone and complete in terms of content</emph>;
                     everything referenced in the body of the page (people, places, bibliography
                     items etc.) is included into the page itself, so that if the page becomes
                     detached from its context (if, for example, someone saves a local copy to use
                     while disconnected from the internet), it will continue to work. This of course
                     means that there is massive duplication of data across the site, but we don’t
                     care. The entire site still comes in smaller than an HD movie.</item>

                  <item><emph>All pages live together in the same folder.</emph> This makes for a
                     very large folder, but it means that linking is trivial and reliable, and URLs
                     are easily remembered and typed.</item>

               </list> Finally, after the website content is generated, all its pages and associated
               CSS files are validated with the W3C’s VNU validator. As always, any invalid file
               causes the build to fail. </p>
            
            <figure xml:id="fig_01">
               <graphic url="img/moemlBuildProcess.png" width="2289px" height="3372px"/>
               <head type="legend">Generation of multiple TEI output formats.</head>
            </figure> 
         </div>

         <div xml:id="advantages">
            <head>Advantages: you can build anything</head>

            <p>A major advantage of building the entire site offline is that we can run processes
               across the entire dataset to build any resource we like, no matter how time- or
               cycle-consuming it may be. A simple example is the <title level="a">A-Z
                  Index,</title> which lists all 9,000 <att>xml:id</att>s used in the project and
               provides information about the entity to which each id refers. This is an essential
               resource for <title level="m">MoEML</title> encoders, who are often creating new
               globally unique <att>xml:id</att>s for entities in the project; having a list of all
                  <att>xml:id</att>s not only prevents duplicates ids, but also ensures that
               encoders can check whether or not the person or place that they are creating already
               exists in the project. Just-in-time creation of the index is not a feasible option:
               the server-side construction of the page, which is nearly 10MB, would be slow, even on a powerful server.
               But, by creating this page ahead of time, the page downloads and
               renders reasonably rapidly. We also produce a plain-text list of all the ids for
               faster access and searching by encoders who may be on a slow internet connection.</p>

            <p>Similarly, it would be impractical to generate the gazetteer of early modern London,
               which aggregates and groups the thousands of variant placenames across the project,
               from the source data on a live server. Before implementing the static build, this
               resource was manually compiled in a semi-automated process. Now we create these
               documents with the rest of the project, which ensures that these documents not only
               reflect the current state of the data, but are also completely valid HTML before they
               are published.</p>

            <p>The offline build also allows us to take advantage of multi-step processes that would
               be very difficult to manage in a just-in-time rendering scenario. We make great use
               of the TEI <gi>rendition</gi>/<att>selector</att> mechanism, which uses CSS selector
               syntax to specify TEI elements to which rendition descriptions apply when encoding
               presentational aspects of the input. In our build process, we use a two step process
               during the creation of the <soCalled>standard</soCalled> XML to resolve these CSS
               selectors. For each document that has a <code>//rendition[@selector]</code>, we
               create a temporary XSLT identity transform that converts the CSS selectors into XPath
               statements, which are then used as the <att>match</att> value for a sequence of
                  <gi>xsl:template</gi> elements. We run that transformation against the source
               document to create the <soCalled>standard</soCalled> version of the XML, adding
                  <att>renditions</att> that correspond with the predefined <gi>rendition</gi> in
               the header. In our standalone process, we then take all <att>style</att> attributes on elements
               and abstract them into <att>rendition</att> pointers to <gi>rendition</gi> elements in the
               header. Then, in our HTML creation, all of the <gi>rendition</gi> elements are turned
               into class selectors in the header of the HTML and, accordingly, all
                  <att>rendition</att> attributes are converted into <att>class</att> values.</p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="disadvantages">
            <head>Disadvantages</head>

            <p>The primary disadvantage of this approach is of course that it involves deferred
               gratification. Builds take a long time, and they often fail to complete due to
               invalidities or other errors. It may be hours before an encoder or author can see the
               results of their work in the context of the built site, and this is particularly
               frustrating for those who are encoding primary source documents and trying to capture
               for reproduction rendering features of the original text.</p>

            <p>However, patience is a virtue and cultivating it is no bad thing. Instant
               gratification is not a feature of scholarly discourse; compared with waiting for a
               journal article to be published, waiting a couple of hours to see the latest draft of
               your document in all its glory is scarcely a hardship. This virtue also extends to
               the discipline around the public release of complete new versions of a site. Rather
               than a <soCalled>rolling release</soCalled> publication model, where on any given
               day, the state of the site is inconsistent, incoherent, and unpredictable, a static
               build process demands a fixed released process, akin to the model of editions of a
               print text; each edition (delimited by project-specific milestones) is clearly
               labelled and identified, and always coherent, consistent, and complete. As we have
               learned from the TEI’s incremental releases of the Guidelines, this is a far superior
               approach, as such releases are much easier to maintain and archive over the long
               term.</p>

            <p>In addition, we do provide shortcuts through the build process for local testing of
               individual files. Our build can be parameterized by supplying one or two specific
               document ids as input, and in that case, the entire build runs for only those
               documents and the results are visible within a minute or so. </p>

         </div>

         <div xml:id="conclusion">
            <head>Conclusion</head>

            <p> We will conclude by summarizing the intent and principles governing our build
               process: <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>Everything that can be pre-fabricated should be pre-fabricated.</item>
                  <item>Everything that could conceivably be useful should be created and
                     included.</item>
                  <item>Redundancy is beneficial; in fact it is elegant. If the same personography
                     entry is replicated in fifty pages that mention that person, then good; any of
                     those pages can now be used outside the context of the collection without
                     loss.</item>
                  <item>Patience is a virtue: let your build take a long time; let your releases be
                     well-separated.</item>
               </list>
            </p>

         </div>

      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <!-- the bibliography for the article, organized as a series of <bibl> elements inside <listBibl> -->
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="arneil_holmes_2017"><author>Arneil, Stewart</author>, and
                     <author>Martin Holmes</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Archiving
                     form and function: preserving a 2003 digital project.</title> DPASSH Conference
                  2017: Digital Preservation for Social Sciences and Humanities, Brighton,
                  UK.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_2017a"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>. <date>2017a</date>.
                     <title level="a">Selecting Technologies for Long-Term Survival.</title> SHARP
                  Conference 2017: Technologies of the Book, Victoria, BC, Canada. <ref
                     target="https://github.com/projectEndings/Endings/raw/master/presentations/SHARP_2017/mdh_sharp_2017.pdf"
                     >https://github.com/projectEndings/Endings/raw/master/presentations/SHARP_2017/mdh_sharp_2017.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_2017b"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>. <date>2017b</date>.
                     <title level="a">Whatever happened to interchange?</title>
                  <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, Volume 32, Issue
                  suppl_1, April 2017, Pages i63–i68. <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw048"
                     >https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw048</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_takeda_2018"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>, and <author>Joseph
                     Takeda</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title level="a">Why do I need four search
                     engines?</title> Japanese Association for Digital Humanities Conference, Tokyo,
                  Japan. <ref
                     target="https://conf2018.jadh.org/files/Proceedings_JADH2018.pdf#page=58"
                     >https://conf2018.jadh.org/files/Proceedings_JADH2018.pdf#page=58</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_takeda_2019"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>, and <author>Joseph
                     Takeda</author>. <date>2019</date>. <title level="a">Beyond Validation: Using
                     Programmed Diagnostics to Learn About, Monitor, and Successfully Complete Your
                     DH Project.</title> In <title level="j">Digital Scholarship in the
                     Humanities</title>. Oxford University Press/EADH. <ref
                     target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqz011"
                     >http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqz011</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="jamstack"><title level="m">JamStack: Modern web development
                     architecture based on client-side JavaScript, reusable APIs, and prebuilt
                     Markup</title>. <date>n.d.</date> https://jamstack.org.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="kirschenbaum_2009"><author>Kirschenbaum, Matthew</author>.
                     <date>2009</date>. <title level="a">Done: Finishing Projects in the Digital
                     Humanities.</title>
                  <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, Volume 3, Issue 2. <ref
                     target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/3/2/000037/000037.html"
                     >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/3/2/000037/000037.html</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="rockwell_et_al_2014"><author>Rockwell, Geoffrey</author>, <author>Shawn
                     Day</author>, <author>Joyce Yu</author>, and <author>Maureen Engel</author>.
                     <date>2014</date>. <title level="a">Burying Dead Projects: Depositing the
                     Globalization Compendium.</title>
                  <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, Volume 8, Issue 2. <ref
                     target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/2/000179/000179.html"
                     >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/2/000179/000179.html</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
