<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body id="compliance" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <h1>Endings Compliance</h1>
    <h2>Deliberately coherent, consistent, complete, versioned, valid, dated, portable, static, no
        server scripting, no databases</h2>
    <main>
        <p style="text-align: center;">
            <img src="img/endings_logo_badge_transparent.svg"
                style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" alt="Transparent Endings logo badge"/>
            <img src="img/endings_logo_badge_dark.svg"
                style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" alt="Dark Endings logo badge"/>
            <img src="img/endings_logo_badge_white.svg"
                style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" alt="Light Endings logo badge"/></p>
        <p>To claim your project's products are Endings-compliant is to promise that they adhere to
            the <a href="principles.html">Endings principles</a>. This means that:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>All code (XML, CSS, HTML, etc.) has been thoroughly validated.</li>
            <li>All internal links have been tested and targets confirmed to exist.</li>
            <li>All internal links are relative, so the site can be hosted anywhere.</li>
            <li>No server-side scripting (PHP, JSP, Python etc.) support is required.</li>
            <li>No backend database software is required.</li>
            <li>Every page on the site carries the same clear edition and date information, so that
                it can be cited effectively.</li>
            <li>There are no external dependencies; or if there are, then they are peripheral to the
                main functionality, and when they fail, the results will not be significant.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>You can <a href="logos.zip">download a package of our logos</a> in various formats, and
            add one to your site, linking to this page.</p>
        <p>We have developed the <a href="principles.html">Endings principles</a> based on the
            results of a five-year research project on the sustainability of digital humanities
            projects. In order to give your projectʼs website the best possible chance of survival;
            and to make it as easy as possible for a library, archive, community organization, or
            other memory institution to assume ownership of the site for long-term preservation
            and/or access; you should have a <q>final state</q> of your website in mind as you begin
            your project (although it is never too late to start this process). For the purposes of
            your research, collaboration, or work, a dynamic website might make perfect sense during
            the duration of your project. But, you should plan adequate resources (time and funding)
            to <q>staticize</q> your site as well as to find a final long-term home for that site
            (in a library, archive, etc.).</p>
    </main>
</body>
