<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body id="people" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <h1>People</h1>
    <h3>Building Sustainable Digital Humanities Projects</h3>
    <main>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="#endings-humanities-faculty">Humanities Faculty</a></li>
            <li><a href="#librarians">Librarians</a></li>
            <li><a href="#programmers">Programmers</a></li>
            <li><a href="#research-assistants">Research Assistants</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p><br/> Over the years, many colleagues and students had a hand in building these various
            projects. Each day we gratefully remember their contributions as we build on their work
            for The Endings Project. </p>
        <h3 id="humanities-faculty">Humanities Faculty</h3>
        <h4 id="claire-carlin">Claire Carlin</h4>
        <h4 id="le-mariage-sous-lancien-régime-marriage-in-early-modern-france">Le Mariage sous
            l’Ancien Régime (Marriage in Early Modern France)</h4>
        <p>A specialist in Early Modern French studies, <strong>Claire Carlin</strong> (PhD,
            University of California) has been a faculty member at UVic from 1989-2015. Her major
            publications focus on the history of theatre and on representations of Early Modern
            marriage. Her specializations include 17th-century theatre, history of marriage in the
            16th-18th centuries, digital humanities, and feminist theory. </p>
        <p>Her research projects include the following:</p>
        <p><strong>Representations of marriage in early modern France</strong>
            <a href="http://mariage.uvic.ca">Le Mariage sous l’Ancien Régime</a> is an ongoing
            digital anthology and scholarly edition funded by SSHRC 2001-2004, 2007-2013. Besides
            numerous articles on this topic, she delivered keynote addresses to the Société pour
            l’Analyse de la Topique Romanesque (SATOR), Université de Paris VII, in 2007 and to the
            joint conference of the Société d’étude du XVIIe siècle, the British Society for
            Seventeenth-Century French Studies, the North American Society for Seventeenth-Century
            French Literature and the Centre international de rencontres sur le XVIIe siècle at
            Oxford University in 2006. She also edited <em>Le Mariage sous l’Ancien Régime</em>,
            special issue of <em>Dalhousie French Studies</em>, 56, fall 2001. </p>
        <p>She has edited Pierre Corneille’s <em>La Veuve</em> and <em>La Suivante</em> for the
                <em>Théâtre complet</em>, vol. I. She has published monographs on Corneille’s
            theatre in 2000 (<em>Women Reading Corneille: Feminist Psychocriticisms of</em> Le Cid)
            and 1998 (<em>Pierre Corneille Revisited</em>). </p>
        <p><strong>History of Medicine</strong> – <em>Imagining Contagion in Early Modern
                Europe</em> (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005) was the result of a project she
            led where each contribution was discussed in depth by the team in a meeting in 2003.
            This project was funded by SSHRC and the Hannah Foundation for the History of Medicine. </p>
        <p><strong>Representations of women in 17th-century France</strong> Ongoing work on
                <em>préciosité</em>, women as writers and readers. </p>
        <p><a href="files/cv_carlin.pdf">Claire Carlin’s CV</a></p>
        <iframe width="838" height="471"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uaCVXdXgNy4?feature=oembed" style="border: 0;"
            allow="fullscreen"/>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="ewa-czaykowska-higgins">Ewa Czaykowska-Higgins</h4>
        <h4 id="the-nxaamxcin-database-and-dictionary">The Nxa’amxcin Database and Dictionary</h4>
        <p><strong>Ewa Czaykowska-Higgins</strong> (PhD, MIT) is a professor in the University of
            Victoria’s Department of Linguistics. Her research focuses primarily on Salish
            languages, and much of her work as a linguist has been as an ally supporting language
            revitalization efforts in several Salish communities. </p>
        <p>Her current work includes participation in a project that examines patterns of intonation
            in four Salish languages: one project aim is the development of a toolkit for describing
            and teaching intonation effectively. She is also involved in the construction of
                <strong>a dictionary and online database of Nxaʔamxčín, an Interior Salish
                language.</strong> The digital component of that project additionally forms one of
            the case studies of Project Endings, a SSHRC-funded investigation of how to make digital
            projects in the humanities more sustainable. </p>
        <p>Czaykowska-Higgins says languages have been an abiding interest, in part because she
            comes from an immigrant-settler family (her native language is Polish). “I just love
            patterns in language. Languages are so deeply interesting in and of themselves. It’s not
            something that most people realize because we use language unconsciously. But when you
            start to look deeper into how languages work, it’s just fascinating.” </p>
        <p>And as a linguist, she understands that language is at the core of who we are and how we
            identify ourselves. “It’s connected to the land, it’s connected to our history, it’s key
            to a lot of political issues—even our <em>spirituality</em> is in language. It’s so
            central to who we are as human beings.” </p>
        <iframe width="838" height="471"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IA-zg71sBgA?feature=oembed" style="border: 0;"
            allow="fullscreen"/>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="janelle-jenstad">Janelle Jenstad</h4>
        <h4 id="the-map-of-early-modern-london">The Map of Early Modern London</h4>
        <p><strong>Janelle Jenstad</strong> (PhD, Queen’s University) associate professor in the
            department of English at the University of Victoria, is the general editor and
            coordinator of <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/">The Map of Early Modern
            London</a>. She is also the assistant coordinating editor of Internet Shakespeare
            Editions. She has taught at Queen’s University, the Summer Academy at the Stratford
            Festival, the University of Windsor, and the University of Victoria. Her articles have
            appeared in the <em>Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies, Early Modern Literary
                Studies, Elizabethan Theatre, Shakespeare Bulletin: A Journal of Performance
                Criticism, and The Silver Society Journal</em>. Her book chapters have appeared (or
            will appear) in <em>Performing Maternity in Early Modern England</em> (Ashgate, 2007),
                <em>Approaches to Teaching Othello</em> (Modern Language Association, 2005),
                <em>Shakespeare, Language and the Stage, The Fifth Wall: Approaches to Shakespeare
                from Criticism, Performance and Theatre Studies</em> (Arden/Thomson Learning, 2005),
                <em>Institutional Culture in Early Modern Society</em> (Brill, 2004), <em>New
                Directions in the Geohumanities: Art, Text, and History at the Edge of Place</em>
            (Routledge, 2011), and <em>Teaching Early Modern English Literature from the
                Archives</em> (MLA, forthcoming). She is currently working on an edition of <em>The
                Merchant of Venice</em> for ISE and Broadview P. She lectures regularly on London
            studies, digital humanities, and on Shakespeare in performance. </p>
        <p><a href="https://janellejenstad.com/">Janelle Jenstad’s Personal Website</a></p>
        <iframe width="838" height="471"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/klkLh76fOc8?feature=oembed" style="border: 0;"
            allow="fullscreen"/>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="elizabeth-grove-white">Elizabeth Grove-White</h4>
        <h4 id="the-robert-graves-diary-project">The Robert Graves Diary Project</h4>
        <p>Following the birth of the first of her four children, <strong>Elizabeth
                Grove-White</strong> (PhD Trinity College Dublin) worked as a researcher, writer,
            editor, and producer at the CBC where she won Canada’s Peabody Award for her
            documentary, “The Longest Journey.” She has taught in Toronto’s Ryerson University as
            well as working for a variety of print and broadcast media in Canada. Her travel pieces
            have appeared in a range of print and digital formats and she remains a frequent
            contributor to the <em>Globe and Mail’s</em> Books section. </p>
        <p>A summer internship as a student reporter with the UK’s <em>Computer Weekly</em>
            newspaper, started Elizabeth’s career-long interest in digital media. She has been
            teaching and researching digital media since 1991 and received SSHRC funding for her
            digital edition of the <a href="https://graves.uvic.ca/">Robert Graves Diary</a> in UVic
            Library’s Special Collections. </p>
        <h3 id="librarians">Librarians</h3>
        <h4 id="corey-davis-systems-librarian">Corey Davis, Systems Librarian</h4>
        <p><strong>Corey Davis</strong> is a Systems Librarian at the University of Victoria and was
            also the Digital Preservation Network Manager from Council of Prairie and Pacific
            University Libraries until 2017. He is currently on the committees of several
            organizations including the Chair of the Web Archiving Group for the Council of Prairie
            and Pacific University Libraries and of the Digital Preservation Working Group at the
            University of Victoria. Also, in 2015 Corey was awarded the Digital Humanities Institute
            Resident Fellowship from the University of Rochester. Corey has a BA with Distinction in
            Greek and Roman Studies from UVic and graduated with a Masters in Library and
            Information Science from UBC in 2003. </p>
        <p><a href="files/cv_davis.pdf">Corey Davis’s CV</a></p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="john-durno-head-of-library-systems">John Durno, Head of Library Systems</h4>
        <p>For the past eleven years, <strong>John Durno</strong> has been Head of Library Systems
            at the University of Victoria, where he manages the exceptional team responsible for
            building and maintaining the Libraries’ IT environment. John’s recent publications
            include Ddgital archaeology and forensics, which includes working with floppy discs from
            the 1980s and Building capacities in digital archaeology. John received a BFA, MFA, and
            MLIS all from the University of British Columbia. His research interests including
            digital forensics, digital archaeology, and any other excuse to muck about with old
            hardware and software. </p>
        <p>Durno’s <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0419-9742">ORCID</a></p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="lisa-goddard-associate-university-librarian-for-digital-scholarship-and-strategy"
            >Lisa Goddard, Associate University Librarian for Digital Scholarship and Strategy</h4>
        <p><strong>Lisa Goddard</strong> is the Associate University Librarian for Digital
            Scholarship and Strategy at University of Victoria Libraries. She holds degrees from
            Queen’s, McGill, and Memorial University, and is currently completing an MA in
            Humanities Computing at the University of Alberta. Lisa’s research interests include
            open access publishing, semantic web technologies, digital publishing &amp;
            preservation, and digital humanities. </p>
        <p>Goddard’s <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4970-053X">ORCID</a></p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="j-matthew-huculak-digital-scholarship-librarian">J. Matthew Huculak, Digital
            Scholarship Librarian</h4>
        <p><strong>Dr. J. Matthew Huculak</strong> is Digital Scholarship Librarian at the
            University of Victoria. He is an Advisory Board Member of Project Muse at Johns Hopkins
            University Press, the Director of the <a href="http://mvp.uvic.ca">Modernist Versions
                Project</a> and co-founder of <a href="https://openmods.uvic.ca">Open
            Modernisms</a>, an open-source web-based resource to share open-access course packs. He
            co-teaches the PreDigital Book course at the [Digital Humanities Summer
            Insitute}(https://dhsi.org) and is former Project Manger at the <a
                href="https://modjourn.org">Modernist Journals Project</a>. With degrees in both
            library science and literature he publishes and teaches at the intersections of
            archives, libraries, book history, modernism, and periodical studies. </p>
        <p>Huculak’s <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2717-1112">ORCID</a>. </p>
        <h3 id="programmers">Programmers</h3>
        <h4 id="martin-holmes-programmer-consultant">Martin Holmes, Programmer Consultant</h4>
        <p><strong>Martin Holmes</strong> has a B.A. (Hons) in English and an MPhil for research in
            Phonology, as well as the RSA/Cambridge Dip. TEFLA. He has taught English as a
            second/foreign language in Britain, Japan, Indonesia, Greece, Saudi Arabia and Canada.
            In the 1990s he moved from teaching into programming with an emphasis on creating online
            language teaching materials and has recently been focusing on both electronic and
            traditional print publishing using XML-based technologies. He is a founder and partner
            (with Stewart Arneil) in Half-Baked Software Inc., a company created with the university
            to commercially exploit software created by Stewart and Martin in the HCMC. He has also
            published several pieces of educational software independently. He was an elected member
            of the Technical Council of the Text Encoding Initiative 2010-2015, and Managing Editor
            of the <i>Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</i> for three years, and was Technical
            Editor of the <i>Scandinavian Canadian Studies Journal</i> for many years. His recent
            projects include the <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca">Map of Early Modern
                London</a>, the <a href="https://bcgenesis.uvic.ca">Colonial Despatches</a>
            collection, the <a href="https://graves.uvic.ca">Robert Graves Diary</a> project, <a
                href="https://mariage.uvic.ca">Le mariage sous L’Ancien Régime</a>, <a
                href="https://dvpp.uvic.ca">Digital Victorian Periodical Poetry</a>, and <a
                href="https://lemdo.uvic.ca/">Linked Early Modern Drama Online</a>. </p>
        <p><a href="https://www.mholmes.com/cv/cv_web.xml">Martin Holmes’s CV</a></p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="stewart-arneil-programmer-consultant">Stewart Arneil, Programmer Consultant</h4>
        <p><strong>Stewart Arneil</strong> is responsible for: creating project specifications,
            supervising workflow for projects, and developing client and server software and
            websites. He also sits on the Digital Humanities committee and ensures that activities
            and operations in the HCMC are consistent with strategic priorities and policies set by
            the committee. </p>
        <p>Stewart has 25 years of experience in both private and public sectors in design,
            management and development of software. He is particularly interested in project design
            and management, language learning, and training people in the appropriate use of
            technology in research, teaching, and learning. </p>
        <p>He holds an M.A. in Computational Theory, certification as an Instructional Designer, and
            a Master’s Certificate in Project Management. </p>
        <p>Stewart is a founder and partner (with Martin Holmes) in Half-Baked Software Inc., a
            company created with the university to take advantage of commercial opportunities for
            software created in part by Stewart in the HCMC. </p>
        <p>In addition to his work on the Endings project, Stewart leads a research cluster and
            coordinates data integration for the Landscapes of Injustice project; he is a developer
            of the Great Unexplained Mysteries in Canadian History website; he maintains and
            upgrades the FrancoToile project; he wrote project specifications, coordinated
            developers and managed contractors on the VIHistory project, and maintains the codebase
            and databases; supervised development of the Capital Trials at the Old Bailey database. </p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="greg-newton">Greg Newton</h4>
        <p><strong>Greg Newton</strong> holds a B.A. (double-major) in English and History, as well
            as a post-degree diploma in Applied Linguistics and a Masters in Education (Educational
            Technology). He is responsible for developing client and server software and websites,
            managing hardware in the HCMC research lab, and maintaining Humanities server
            infrastructure in co-operation with Research Computing. </p>
        <p>In addition to the Endings Project, Greg’s current projects include <a
                href="https://myths.uvic.ca/">Myths on Maps</a> and the <a
                href="https://cgwp.uvic.ca/">Canadian Great War Project</a></p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="joseph-takeda-junior-programmerresearch-assistant">Joseph Takeda,
            Programmer/Research Assistant</h4>
        <p><strong>Joseph Takeda</strong> received his BA (Honours with Distinction) in English and
            Women’s Studies from the University of Victoria in 2016, and his MA in English (Science
            and Technology Research Stream) from the University of British Columbia in 2021. In
            2016, Joseph was awarded the Department of English Medal of Excellence and the SSHRC
            CGS-M (UBC). His recent publications include “Making the RA Matter: Pedagogy, Interface,
            and Practices” written with Janelle Jenstad and “The MoEML Finding Aid to the Bills of
            Mortality”. He was a Programmer on The Endings Project, and is co-author of the
            staticSearch project. He is currently a User Interface Developer at the Digital
            Humanities Innovation Lab (Simon Fraser University). </p>
        <h3 id="research-assistants">Research Assistants</h3>
        <h4 id="emily-comeau-researcher">Emily Comeau, Researcher</h4>
        <p><strong>Emily Comeau</strong> completed her MA in Linguistics in 2018 at the University
            of Victoria, where her research explored the role of literacy in Indigenous language
            revitalization and the implications of print literacy for decolonization. She also has a
            BA in Linguistics and International Studies from the University of Alberta. She
            began her doctoral program at UBCO in fall 2021. Emily has been working on the Endings
            Project and Le Mariage Sous L¹Ancien Régime since 2017. </p>
        <h4 id="sarah-kell-researcher">Sarah Kell, Researcher</h4>
        <p><strong>Sarah Kell</strong> has a BA in Linguistics and a MEd in Indigenous Language
            Revitalization, both from the University of Victoria. She has been co-editor of the
            Nxaʔamxčín Database and Dictionary since 2010. Sarah also assists UVic linguists with
            research on other Salish languages and consults on Indigenous language curriculum
            development with First Nations, school districts, and the BC Ministry of Education. </p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="daniel-martin-researcher">Daniel Martin, Researcher</h4>
        <p><strong>Daniel Martin</strong> was an MA student in English. His research considered the
            relationship between creative pedagogy and first year composition courses - this project
            was supported by a teaching and learning scholarship from the Centre for Teaching and
            learning at UVic. He also holds a BA in English and Writing from the University of Leeds
            and a Post-Graduate Certificate in Education from the University of Teesside in the UK.
            Daniel worked on the Endings project from July to November 2018. </p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="tye-landels-gruenewald-researcher">Tye Landels-Gruenewald, Researcher</h4>
        <p><strong>Tye Landels-Gruenewald</strong> was an undergraduate at UVic studying for an
            English major (Honors with Distinction) and European Studies minor, and then went on to
            take an MA at Queen’s University. He is also a past President of the English Students’
            Society and the 2014 3M National Student Fellowship Recipient. As an English Honours
            student, Tye turned his passion for geography and urban studies to helping create the
            Map of Early Modern London. </p>
        <hr/>
        <h4 id="jennifer-polack-research-assistant">Jennifer Polack, Research Assistant</h4>
        <p><strong>Jennifer Polack</strong> was an undergraduate student studying for her BA
            (English Major, Professional Communications Minor) at the University of Victoria. She
            worked as a co-op student for The Endings Project. Her previous co-op positions include
            a fundraising coordinator for the Victoria Native Friendship Centre and editorial
            assistant on the International Journal of Indigenous Health. She is also a social media
            and content developer for Animikii, Inc. </p>
    </main>
</body>
