<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body id="projects" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <h1>Projects</h1>
    <h3>Building Sustainable Digital Humanities Projects</h3>
    <main>

        <p>The Endings project began with a portfolio of four long-running University of Victoria
            projects as test cases for developing our guidelines, principles and approaches for
            achieving sustainability:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="https://graves.uvic.ca">The Robert Graves Diary</a></li>
            <li>The Nxa’amxcín Database and Dictionary (currently not public)</li>
            <li><a href="https://mariage.uvic.ca/">Le Mariage sous l’Ancien Régime</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca">The Map of Early Modern London</a></li>
        </ul>
        <p>These original projects are described below. As the Endings work has proceeded, other digital
            projects have been <q>adopted</q> as Endings exemplars:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="https://majw.uvic.ca/">Medieval Anglo-Jewish Women</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://francotoile.uvic.ca">Francotoile</a></li>
            <!--<li><a href="http://mvp.uvic.ca">Modernist Versions Project</a></li>-->
            <li><a href="https://bcgenesis.uvic.ca">The Colonial Despatches of Vancouver Island and
                    British Columbia</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://myndir.uvic.ca">My Norse Digital Image Repository</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://johnkeats.uvic.ca">Mapping Keat’s Progress</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://loi.uvic.ca/archive/">The Landscapes of Injustice Archive</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://winnifredeatonarchive.org/">The Winnifred Eaton Archive</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://dvpp.uvic.ca">Digital Victorian Periodical Poetry</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://lemdo.uvic.ca/">Linked Early Modern Drama Online (LEMDO)</a> (site
                still under development)</li>
            <li>Kwakwendahchondiahk: Projet de dictionnaire wendat | Wendat Dictionary Project 
                (site not yet public)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>And of course this Endings site itself is naturally Endings-compliant:</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li><a href="https://endings.uvic.ca/">The Endings Project</a></li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>Most of these projects are still very much in their prime, and one or two of them are
            only just getting started. In fact, it is much easier to design a project from scratch
            with longevity in mind than it is to rescue or re-work an old project which has been
            active for a long time. One additional project, the <i>Scandinavian Canadian Studies
                Journal</i>, was originally an Endings site, but due to a change of editorship it is
            now hosted elsewhere and is no longer Endings-compliant.</p>
        
        <div id="map-of-early-modern-london">
        <h3>Map of Early Modern London</h3>
        <p>The Map of Early Modern London (<a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/index.htm"
            >MoEML</a>) has four distinct projects:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>a digital edition of the <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/map.htm">1561 Agas
                    woodcut map of London</a>;</li>
            <li>an <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtEncyclopedia.htm?listType=subcategory"
                    >Encyclopedia</a> and <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/gazetteer_a.htm"
                    >Descriptive Gazetteer</a> of London people, places, topics, and terms;</li>
            <li>a <a
                    href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtPrimarySourceLibrary.htm?listType=subcategory"
                    >Library</a> of marked-up texts rich in London toponyms;</li>
            <li>and a versioned edition of John Stow’s <a
                    href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/stow.htm">Survey of London</a>.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>These four projects draw data from MoEML’s five databases:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>a <a
                    href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtEncyclopediaLocation.htm?listType=subcategory"
                    >Placeography</a> of locations (e.g., streets, sites, playhouses, taverns,
                churches, wards, and topographical features);</li>
            <li>a <a
                    href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtEncyclopediaPersonography.htm?listType=subcategory"
                    >Personography</a> of early modern Londoners, both historical and literary;</li>
            <li>an <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtEncyclopediaOrganization.htm"
                    >Orgography</a> of organizations (e.g., livery companies and other
                corporations);</li>
            <li>a <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/GLOSS1.htm">Bibliography</a> of primary and
                secondary sources;</li>
            <li>and a <a href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/GLOSS1.htm">Glossary</a> of terms
                relevant to early modern London.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Map of Early Modern London is on <a href="https://www.twitter.com/MoEMLondon">Twitter</a>
            and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/The-Map-of-Early-Modern-London/317355293645"
                >Facebook</a>. Check out our <a
                href="https://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/mdtParatextBlogPost.htm">blog</a> for updates and
            to find out more about the project.</p>
        <h3 id="in-the-news">In the News</h3>
        <p><a
                href="https://www.citylab.com/equity/2015/04/an-interactive-map-of-shakespeares-london/390060/"
                >April 9, 2015 – “An Interactive Map of Shakespeare’s London” by Tanvi Misra</a></p>
        <p><a
                href="http://www.ctvnews.ca/lifestyle/interactive-maps-show-travellers-shakespeare-s-london-hugo-s-france-1.2323442"
                >April 12, 2015 – “Interactive maps show travellers Shakespeare’s London, Hugo’s
                France”</a></p>
        <p><a
                href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/shakespeare-s-london-mapped-online-by-uvic-researchers-1.3046122"
                >Apr 23, 2015 – “Shakespeare’s London mapped online by UVic researchers”</a></p></div>
        
        <div id="le-mariage-sous-lancien-régime-marriage-in-early-modern-france">
        <h3>Le Mariage sous
            l’Ancien Régime (Marriage in Early Modern France)</h3>
        <p lang="en">Should one marry? The question posed by Rabelais’s Panurge proved inescapable in the West, especially from the time of the Counter-Reformations onwards. From the beginnings of the Council of Trent in 1545 to the end of the reign of Louis XIV in 1715, attempts to renew marriage in France came up against the growing intervention of the monarchy in an institution that had previously been dominated by the Church. The encounter between these two authorities was tumultuous, but it was also conducive to the proliferation of documents that are the subject of this site: the <q>nuptial imaginary</q> is made up of various textual genres, each with its own character, but all dealing with fears, desires and fantasies about the marital union in the context of the major upheavals in religious, political, social and cultural thought and practices of early modernity (16th-18th centuries).</p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Doit-on se marier ? La question de Panurge s’avère incontournable en Occident, surtout à partir des Contre-réformes. Des débuts du Concile de Trente en 1545 jusqu’à la fin du règne de Louis XIV en 1715, les tentatives de renouveler le mariage se heurtent en France à l’intervention croissante de la monarchie dans cette institution dominée auparavant par l’Église. La rencontre entre ces deux autorités fut tumultueuse mais propice au foisonnement des documents qui font l’objet de ce site : l’imaginaire nuptial se compose de divers genres textuels, chacun ayant son caractère propre, mais tous traitant des peurs, des désirs et des fantasmes au sujet de l’union conjugale dans le contexte des grands remous dans la pensée et les pratiques religieuses, politiques, sociales et culturelles de la première modernité (XVIe-XVIIIe siècles).   
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                This virtual anthology is first and foremost rooted in polemical discourse on marriage, which is divided into three chronological sections. Between around 1570 and 1630, misogynist and misogamist satire flourished: the topoi of the Middle Ages were renewed through pseudo-scientific glosses on medical discourse and cultural comparisons inspired by the travel literature of explorers. Traditional historical and mythological allusions were also revived to fuel criticism of women and marriage. When this <q>new polemics</q> disappeared from the world of textual publishing in the 1630s, the satire directed against shrews and their cuckolded husbands was recovered in engravings; we have provided over 70 examples. Relegated to these popular images until the last quarter of the century, satire on women and marriage was again revived in certain works of fiction and in the theatre from the 1680s onwards.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Cette anthologie virtuelle est tout d’abord ancrée dans la parole polémique relative au mariage, déployée en trois tranches chronologiques. Entre 1570 environ et 1630, la satire misogyne et misogame connaît une floraison importante : les topoi du Moyen Âge se renouvellent grâce à des gloses pseudo-savantes sur le discours médical et des comparaisons culturelles inspirées par les récits de voyage d’exploration. Les allusions historiques et mythologiques traditionnelles sont également ravivées pour mieux alimenter la critique des femmes et du mariage. Quand cette nouvelle polémique disparaît du monde de l’édition textuelle aux années 1630, la satire dirigée contre les mégères et leurs maris cocus se récupère dans les gravures ; nous en fournissons plus de 70 exemples. Reléguée à ces images populaires jusqu’au dernier quart du siècle, la satire de la femme et du mariage fait encore peau neuve dans certains ouvrages de fiction et au théâtre dès les années 1680.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                While misogyny was present in varying degrees in the criticism of marriage throughout the century, the valorization of wives was evident in the textual production emanating from the salons, especially from the 1650s onwards under the influence of the movement known as <i>Préciosité</i>. The celebration of women received a further boost when fairy tales became fashionable at the turn of the eighteenth century; in both cases, the success of women writers was a key element. Between the 1640s and 1670s, even Catholic treatises on marriage praised women and supported both members of the couple in the face of the challenges of marriage, which was usually arranged.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Si la misogynie est présente à divers degrés dans la critique du mariage tout au long du siècle, la valorisation des épouses se manifeste dans la production textuelle émanant des salons, ce surtout à partir des années 1650 sous l’influence du mouvement précieux. La célébration de la femme connaît un nouvel élan lorsque les contes de fée deviennent à la mode au tournant du XVIIIe siècle ; dans les deux cas, le succès des écrivaines y est pour beaucoup. Entre les années 1640 et 1670, même les traités catholiques sur le mariage font l’éloge de la femme et soutiennent les deux membres du couple devant le défi que représente le mariage, la plupart du temps forcé. 
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                By the end of the seventeenth century, however, Catholic treatises and worldly discourse reverted to a distrust of women as responsible for the evils of marriage, a reflection of the trend we see in novels and theatre too. The tension between these two trends intensified: some texts and images emphasized women's moral weakness, while others stress women's strength of character and creativity. What they have in common is a scathing critique of the institution of marriage.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Toujours est-il qu’à la fin du XVIIe siècle, les traités catholiques et le discours mondain reviennent à la méfiance de la femme tenue responsable des maux du mariage, un reflet du courant que nous observons dans les romans et au théâtre aussi. La tension entre ces deux tendances s’intensifie : certains textes et images soulignent la faiblesse morale de la femme tandis que d’autres insistent sur la force de caractère et la créativité féminines. Ce qu’elles ont en commun est une critique acerbe de l’institution du mariage. 
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                The examination of marriage since the sixteenth century, developed from various angles in the seventeenth, prepared the ground for the emerging models of the eighteenth century: on the one hand, the easy divorce, freed from traditional Catholic constraints, proposed by certain jurists even before the Revolution; on the other, the love matches and harmonious family relationships affecting all levels of society. These divergent visions are the result of the evolution of ideas about married life throughout early modernity – ideas that persist in various forms today.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                La mise en examen du mariage depuis le XVIe siècle, développée sous divers angles au XVIIe, a préparé le terrain aux modèles émergents du XVIIIe siècle : d’une part, le divorce facile, libéré des contraintes catholiques traditionnelles, proposé par certains juristes même avant la Révolution ; de l’autre, le portrait du mariage amoureux et des relations de famille harmonieuses touchant à tous les niveaux sociaux. Ces imaginaires divergents sont le fruit de l’évolution des idées sur l’union conjugale tout au long de la première modernité – des idées qui persistent sous différentes formes de nos jours.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                Please note that the aim of this anthology is not only to create a corpus of texts and images of marriage during the <i>Ancien Régime</i>, but also to explore the potential of virtual scholarly publishing, hence the regular addition of notes, references linked to our index of proper names, bibliographical entries, links to resources external to the site, articles commenting on the corpus, and textual analyses using our search engine. Le mariage sous l’Ancien Régime is also a case study in The Endings Project: Concluding, Archiving, and Preserving Digital Projects for Long-Term Usability, funded, as was the anthology, by the Insight program of the <a href="https://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/">Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada</a>.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Il est à noter que cette anthologie a pour but non seulement de créer un corpus de textes et d’images au sujet du mariage sous l’Ancien Régime, mais aussi d’explorer les potentialités de l’édition savante virtuelle, d’où le rajout à un rythme régulier de notes, de références reliés à notre index de noms propres, d’entrées bibliographiques, de liens à des ressources externes au site, d’articles commentant le corpus et d’analyses textuelles grâce à notre engin de recherche. Le mariage sous l’Ancien Régime est aussi un étude de cas participant au projet <a href="https://endings.uvic.ca/">Endings: Concluding, Archiving, and Preserving Digital Projects for Long-Term Usability</a>, financé, comme l’anthologie l’a été, par le programme Savoir du <a href="https://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/">Conseil de recherches en sciences humaines du Canada</a>.
            </p>
            
            <p lang="en">
                Reproduction rights for the engravings were purchased from the Bibliothèque Nationale de France. The other elements of the site (the contributions of the editors, the transcriptions of the texts, the encoding and the code) are distributed under the terms of this licence: <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/deed.en">Creative Commons Attribution - Noncommercial - No Derivative Works 4.0 Canada</a>. 
            </p>
            
            <p lang="fr">
                Les droits de reproduction des gravures ont été achetés à la Bibliothèque Nationale de France. Les autres éléments du site (les contributions des éditeurs, les transcriptions des textes, l'encodage et le code) sont distribués sous les termes de cette licence : <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/deed.fr">Creative Commons - Attribution - Pas d’Utilisation Commerciale - Pas de Modification 4.0 Canada</a>.
            </p>
        
        </div>
        
        <div id="Nxaʔamxčín-database-and-dictionary">
        
        <h3>Nxaʔamxčín Database and Dictionary</h3>
        <p>This is a database of words and phrases from the Nxaʔamxčín language (sometimes referred
            to in English as Moses, or Moses-Columbia Salish). The purpose of this database is to
            pull together all the materials on Nxaʔamxčín compiled by M. Dale Kinkade and Ewa
            Czaykowska-Higgins, two linguists who worked closely with native speakers of the
            language. The goals of the project are as follows:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>to make these materials available and easily accessible to the Nxaʔamxčín community,
                rather than to leave them stored on file cards and in notebooks;</li>
            <li>to serve as a searchable tool for learners, teachers, speakers, and linguists;</li>
            <li>to serve as a source for Nxaʔamxčín vocabulary and phrases;</li>
            <li>to serve as a source for creating a Nxaʔamxčín Dictionary in print format.</li>
            <li>to serve as a model for the role of digitization in language preservation and
                revitalization.</li>
        </ul>
        
        </div>
        
        <div id="robert-graves-diary">
        <h3>Robert Graves Diary</h3>
        <p>The University of Victoria digital edition of the Robert Graves Diary has long been seen as a
            pioneering XML publication project. Beginning with a pilot markup project in 2001 (still
            used as an example for training purposes by the TEI), it evolved into a complete edition
            of the diaries of Robert Graves from the period 1935 to 1939 and was one of the first
            projects built on the now widely used eXist XML database system. A collaboration between
            the University of Victoria’s English department, the HCMC, and UVic Libraries (whose
            Special Collections holds the original manuscript), it has been widely cited and
            referenced as a model project in the field of Digital Humanities since its first
            publication in 2004. The database was shared successfully with Trinity College
            Dublin. The site has been rewritten to be Endings-compliant, and was the first of
            our Endings sites to be transitioned to long-term archive hosting at the University
            of Victoria Library.
        </p>
        </div>
        
    </main>
</body>
