<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body id="symposium" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <h1>The Endings 2021 Symposium</h1>
    <h2>A Virtual Event</h2>
    <main>
        <p>As part of our <a href="https://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/home-accueil-eng.aspx">Social
                Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC)</a> grant, the Endings
            Project organized a symposium which was held online in April 2021. This event brought
            together eight of the people we interviewed in depth as part of our earlier survey to
            talk about their experiences and insights into digital longevity. Out of the symposium
            will come a <a href="dhq.html">special issue</a> of the <i>Digital Humanities
                Quarterly</i>.</p>
        <p>The symposium was open to anyone, and had a large number of attendees.</p>
        
        <h3>Presentation abstracts</h3>
        
        <details> 
                  <summary>Constance Crompton: Data Preparation: Striving to Balance Sustainability and Innovation</summary> 
                  <p>The tide is shifting in research data management and preservation. There is a move
                     away from innovation-only funding opportunities, but as yet, few funding streams are
                     available to maintain the digital scholarship whose development has been grant funded.
                     My conversation, entitled <q>Data Preparation: Striving to Balance Sustainability and
                        Innovation</q> outlines the process of data preparation in the Lesbian and Gay Liberation
                     in Canada (LGLC) project starting in 2013, in the face of funding guidelines that
                     favoured, at the time, novelty over long-term preservation. Much has changed in research
                     data management in the intervening years, with the balance shifting toward data management
                     plans and the adoption of standards. This talk will invite a discussion of best practices
                     for meeting funder requirements while planning for a project whose long-term maintenance
                     may not have financial or institutional support.</p> 
                  <p>This conversation takes as its departure a small aside in the responses to Ed Folsom’s
                     <q>Database as Genre: The Epic Transformation of Archives</q> published in the PMLA in
                     2007, in which he suggested that databases and narrative are intrinsically opposed.</p> 
                  <p>In response to Folsom’s polemic, Jerome McGann was left wondering where TEI-XML stood
                     in the PMLA debate on about databases, especially considering that Folsom’s largest
                     Digital Humanities project, the Walt Whitman Archive, is a TEI-based project. His
                     response to Folsom, <q>Database, Interface, and Archival Fever,</q> outlines his two difficulties
                     with Folsom’s articulation. The first difficulty, according to McGann is what he calls
                     a <q>loose way of thinking about our paper-based inheritance as well as about these
                        new digital technologies</q> (158). Folsom and Price’s Walt Whitman Archive is not, McGann
                     notes, a database (which Folsom protests, praising Hayles for showing how vital metaphors
                     are, and describing the term database as a <q>metaphor, a base onto which we put things
                        that are given (data).</q> (1608)); more accurately, it is an online archive driven by
                     <q>an inline markup structure (XML) and an XSL-generated interface</q> (1588). Parts of
                     the Walt Whitman Archive do run off a MySQL database, but McGann’s point holds – the
                     project is a TEI-based one, not a database-based one. McGann also undermines the idea
                     of database as the ultimate tool of the twenty-first century by proposing that <q>for
                        scholars interested in migrating our cultural inheritance to digital environments…
                        TEI and XML … are better [than database models] because they model some of the key
                        forms of order that are already embedded in textual works like Whitman’s … [and] because
                        they understand that works like poems and novels are already marked data</q> — while
                     acknowledging that TEI and XML are not wholly sufficient to represent data for scholarly
                     purposes (1589).</p> 
                  <p>Fifteen years after this debate in the PMLA, with the new cultural engagement with
                     sustainability and research data management, McGann’s arguments are perhaps more prescient
                     than ever. TEI-backed linked data may prove to be realisation of his vision of the
                     ultimate tool of the twenty-first century Humanities scholarship specifically because,
                     unlike databases or dynamic visualisations, it is easily archived. TEI’s readily achievability,
                     exchangeability, and its potential to contribute to the semantic web mean that it
                     stands a good chance of contributing to future knowledge. This conversation will conclude
                     with suggestions for encouraging the use of sustainable formats and reflections on
                     how the LGLC project members hope the LGLC data might be preserved, but also how it
                     might contribute to future scholarship.</p> 
                  <h3>Works Cited</h3> 
                  <p>Freedman, J., Hayles, N.K., McGann, J., McGill, M.L., Stallybrass, P., Folsom, E.,
                     2007. Responses to Ed Folsom’s 'Database as Genre: The Epic Transformation of Archives.'
                     <i>PMLA</i> 122, 1580–1612. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1632/pmla.2007.122.5.1580">https://doi.org/10.1632/pmla.2007.122.5.1580</a></p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>James Cummings: Adventures in Hosting and Storage</summary> 
                  <p>To avoid fragility, online digital projects require stable hosting, regular maintenance,
                     and backup; to avoid disappearing, they need proper archiving. This session will consider
                     some of the problems of Hosting, Maintenance, Backup, and Long-term Storage. Having
                     had experiences from the perspectives of the academic, the developer, and the project
                     manager on digital projects, James Cummings will present some examples of problems
                     that can – and have – occurred in these four key areas.</p> 
                  <p>(1) Hosting problems include a wide range of possible stumbling blocks. From even
                     getting sufficient access to appropriate institutional server space (once described
                     by Miriam Posner as the hardest computing problem in the world) to the problems caused
                     by the inevitable march of technology. Some issues encountered include the unexpected
                     change of platforms and software; the disappearance of servers; inadvisable personal
                     hosting by the researcher, without institutional support or access; and the challenges
                     for an institution hosting a project whose leader has left in one way or another.</p> 
                  <p>(2) Maintenance problems seem inevitable as all projects, however minimal, need some
                     maintenance to at very least their infrastructure. While the guidelines of The Endings
                     Project are an important and laudable goal, historically most projects aren’t as proactive
                     in the planning stages of lessening the maintenance burden which will arise as a result
                     after the project has concluded. Sometimes this happens when a project relies on individual
                     rather than institutional infrastructure, or when a project is orphaned for whatever
                     reason within an institution, or when basic software and hardware updates and security
                     patches are not done.</p> 
                  <p>(3) Backup problems one would think would be a thing of the past in a day when digital
                     backup can be seamless and transparent. Although there are still many instances where
                     materials cannot be backed up for legal reasons, in most cases it is not that backup
                     can’t be done but that it hasn’t been done or has been done poorly. There may be no
                     physical, archival copies of data alongside the digital copies, or the location of
                     backups is insecure or unknown. Individuals may feel backing up to Dropbox on a single
                     project member’s account is sufficient, or that placing their materials in a close
                     repository which limits access is acceptable.</p> 
                  <p>(4) Long-term storage continues to be a problem and there are some choices a project
                     can make which makes their long-term preservation for later re-use more of a possibility.
                     Problems tend to occur when inadvisable technical choices (such as file-format selection)
                     have been made along the way, or when a project’s focus on interface or functionality
                     (e.g., search functions) has delayed or complicated the storage of essential data.
                     The most common limitation is when after the project is done, the data is only preserved
                     in, and accessible from, a single repository.</p> 
                  <p>Cummings will give examples of a small number of projects in which some of these problems
                     have been evident, and what these projects did – or should have done – to mitigate
                     the effects.</p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Sara Diamond: The Danger of Disappearance</summary> 
                  <p>What happens—or can happen—when, after creating online resources, institutional leadership
                     changes, archival web sites are taken down through redesign or rebranding? This may
                     occur with non-traditional collectors or large institutions. What are the rights of
                     the institution versus those who created, recorded, and prepared the material for
                     display? What are the rights of funders, and the general public? What special challenges
                     can develop if vulnerable populations are involved, for example, Indigenous groups
                     concerned with cultural preservation, or students whose career prospects are potentially
                     damaged when access to material they helped create disappears? What are the best practices
                     to ensure that the rights of all involved are protected? And if even best practices
                     fail to guarantee rights, what strategies might be put in place to mitigate damage
                     done?</p> 
                  <p>A significant case study, the Banff New Media Institute will be provided with two
                     other case studies, the Daniel Langlois Foundation archives and the Women’s Labour
                     History Archives.</p> 
                  <p>The Banff New Media Institute (1995 - 2010), located at The Banff Centre in Alberta,
                     Canada, was an international think tank on the present and future practices of new
                     media, a training hub, co-production centre, business incubator and accelerator, and
                     a comprehensive research infrastructure and residency program, and exhibition curator.
                     Over the course of its first ten years it held over 150 summits, symposia, workshops,
                     conferences and events which were recorded and relevant records such as release forms,
                     agendas, analysis of events and other memorabilia kept. These events brought together
                     leaders from around the globe who were engaged in developing the science, creative
                     practices, jurisprudence, business models, design practices and theories in the emerging
                     new media world. The BNMI ensured strong representation of women and diverse presenters.
                     A feature of BNMI was its deep commitment to Indigenous creators and technical leaders
                     through inclusion at its events and within its research and co-production, and in
                     collaboration with local Indigenous communities. Co-productions were described and
                     catalogued, and the documentation made available on-line, as were exhibition descriptions
                     and documentation through the Walter Philips Gallery and in physical form. The BNMI
                     also created Horizonzero.ca an online gallery, commissioning environment, and site
                     for analysis of the emerging new media world with a focus on Canadian practices within
                     a global context. It provided a site of reflection for the BNMI activities (for example
                     nano technology creative research) but stretched well beyond its boundaries.</p> 
                  <p>I raised the resources and rallied the personnel in collaboration with Susan Kennard
                     (BNMI Director from 2005 – 2010) and Manager before that time and researcher and curator
                     Sarah Cook, to create The Banff New Media Institute archives in 2004-5 as I was leaving
                     my job as Founding Director of the Banff New Media Institute (BNMI). We received significant
                     support from Telefilm, the Canada Council for the Arts, Heritage Canada, and Library
                     and Archives Canada. At the completion of the project all audio files from summits
                     and workshops were available on-line as well as all event agendas, biographies of
                     presenters, many papers that were provided, and event analysis. The on-line archive
                     was easy to navigate and search. A physical archive with finding aides was created
                     which held the corresponding catalogues, BNMI brochures, and all manner of planning
                     documents.</p> 
                  <p>Sarah Cook and I created a book, <i>Euphoria &amp; Dystopia: the Banff New Media Institute Dialogues</i> (2011. Banff Centre Press &amp; Riverside Architectural Press) which chronicled and analyzed
                     the global era of the Banff New Media Institute, the Institute itself through commissioned
                     essays, and provided analysis of six themes that ran through the ten years, excerpts
                     from the summits and workshops as well as detail in a comprehensive appendix of events
                     and attendees. It also included a DVD of Horizonzero.ca. An e-publication followed
                     two years later, with hotlinks throughout to the BNMI archives.</p> 
                  <p>Five years ago, during a change of leadership, new institutional strategy and web
                     site redesign, The Banff Centre took the entire archives down, all the co-production
                     information and any mention that the BNMI had existed at The Banff Centre. In 2019
                     The Banff Centre chose not to renew Horizonzero.ca. The Banff Centre is now reconsidering
                     the value of the BNMI and its archive as it builds its digital renewal.</p> 
                  <p>The Daniel Langlois Foundation archives was funded by Daniel Langlois the co-founder
                     of Softimage. It became an important repository for the many new media art works funded
                     by the foundation and had an excellent physical and web presence. After a decade Langlois’s
                     interests moved on and the archive was closed. It took many years for it to find a
                     new home, to the disappointment of artists and scholars.</p> 
                  <p>The talk will address questions of responsibilities and rights in these two instances.
                     The strategy for the current creation of the Women’s Labour History Archive with VIVO,
                     an artist-run centre and Simon Fraser University, reflects lessons from these two
                     examples.</p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Jan Marontate: 	
                     Documentation and Transformations in Digital Preservation</summary> 
                  <p>When funded scientific or creative projects end, records and work remain. Today these
                     records are often ‘born digital’ or include some work converted from analogue to digitized
                     formats. Records preserved in digital media are not only of interest for the legacy
                     of projects that have ended, but can constitute a continuing resource for future scientific
                     or creative activity. In this session, Dr. Marontate explores how diverse (and sometimes
                     incommensurate) value systems embedded in technologies and in values of practitioners
                     raise challenges for digital preservation.</p> 
                  <p>Designers of projects for digital preservation with resilience for future uses face
                     challenges in anticipating and understanding changing forms of digital media. Technologies
                     used in creation and preservation of digital media shape both creative practices and
                     conservation activities. When technologies change, records of past work and established
                     practices, even very recent ones, may be lost or altered or become unviable. Even
                     recent work (such as statistical data sets or videos) may become unusable and inaccessible
                     when software programs are upgraded or new hardware replaces old. Computer upgrades
                     and transformations in equipment have become commonplace events. Most computer users
                     have experienced loss or change in data when they adopt new systems. Modifications
                     to the <q>original</q> may have serious consequences, rendering valuable work and data sets meaningless
                     or indecipherable. How often do we discard old work or data sets because they are
                     difficult or impossible to use with new software or equipment? When technical practices
                     change, new assumptions and values may emerge about the meaning of the collections.</p> 
                  <p>Yet, information about the values of people involved in creation and preservation
                     activities is often fragmentary and incomplete. Even within a single project creators,
                     researchers, archivists and conservators may prioritize different qualities. These
                     values have an impact on what is created and how it is preserved. It is not always
                     possible to gather such information later. Creators of images, texts and sonic materials
                     eventually disappear. Even when they are still alive their recollections and priorities
                     may change. Researchers, technicians and research assistants move on. Documentation
                     of the work of creators and collaborators (including people providing technical support)
                     may not include the information needed for maintenance of the full range of features
                     of materials in the preservation of digital collections.</p> 
                  <p>How can digital preservation acknowledge the multiple meanings of works for creators,
                     and the activities of various types of team members involved in both the creation
                     of digital materials and the preservation of archives? How are decisions made about
                     what to preserve and how to document it? What are the implications of such decisions
                     for long-term maintenance of digital media? Some types of digital works, such as audio-visual
                     materials (like sound recordings) may present specific features for preservation activities,
                     for example, as new technologies are developed to allow greater flexibility, larger
                     data sets and different playback options.</p> 
                  <p>The polysemy (that is, multiple meanings) of digital works presents challenges. The
                     works preserved themselves may have different meanings for originators or creators,
                     and for people involved in preservation. Pragmatic approaches in French cultural sociology
                     suggest ways of taking diverse (and sometimes competing) value systems into account
                     in digital preservation initiatives. These approaches do not establish normative principles.
                     The goal of studying meanings in the generation and conservation of digital media
                     is not to determine what to preserve or how to conserve digital media. Rather the
                     goal is to identify how diverse value systems and multiple meanings of works influence
                     digital media preservation.</p> 
                  <p>Dr. Marontate begins with a brief reflection on ways of studying the interplay of
                     symbolic and material dimensions in digital documentation practices. These include
                     analysis of many types of activities, among them: changing technologies and their
                     impact on features of digital collections, new facilities for embedding documentation
                     in metadata, and ways that varying values shape both the creation of works and their
                     preservation. Examples of preservation activities illustrate how the 'meanings' or
                     socio-cultural significance of activities are preserved in digital formats. Digital
                     archives that include historic materials may raise specific questions too, since multiple
                     processes may have transformed materials over time. Next, she considers innovative
                     theoretical and methodological frameworks for analysing value systems proposed by
                     Nathalie Heinich, based on studies of conflicting value systems by Luc Boltanski and
                     Laurent Thévenot. Debates in archival and conservation networks also illustrate the
                     multiple challenges in crafting memories of past for the future. She concludes with
                     a critical analysis of the potential uses of studies of changing technologies and
                     values for understanding and designing digital media preservation.</p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Jessica Otis: Follow the Money</summary> 
                  <p>While some digital humanities (DH) projects can be undertaken with free software and
                     whatever time a scholar already has to hand, larger and more collaborative projects
                     generally need additional resources. In the traditional book- and article-based humanistic
                     workflows, universities, colleges, archives, special collections, publishers, and
                     libraries have established labor and funding models that aim to support text-based
                     research, writing, publishing, distribution, and preservation pipelines. But DH projects—collaborative
                     or otherwise—rarely fit into these pipelines and subsequently cannot readily avail
                     themselves of these preexisting labor and funding models. The path towards a collaborative
                     DH project instead requires scholars to invent funding, often at every stage of their
                     project's lifecycle. Like other humanists whose institutions fail to provide them
                     with sufficient funding for their scholarship, many digital humanists turn towards
                     self-funding to cover part or even all of their project costs. But when self-funding
                     becomes infeasible, as it often does with larger and more collaborative projects,
                     digital humanists typically turn towards grant-writing.</p> 
                  <p>Grants might seem like the optimal solution to digital humanists' funding problems,
                     as they entail receiving funding for a specific length of time to generate a specific
                     project, much as other humanists are funded to visit a specific archive or come under
                     contract to write a specific book. A variety of funders often grants for the creation
                     of digital projects, which makes it relatively easy to align a scholarly agenda with
                     the agenda of those funders in order to create something mutually beneficial. Furthermore,
                     grants come with numerous additional benefits, including a peer review process that
                     helps to establish the digital project's scholarly value prior to the investment of
                     significant time and money; built-in project publicity from the grant funding announcement;
                     and institutionally internal and external prestige for having won a grant. University
                     and college administrators are particularly pleased with humanists' growing ability
                     to join scientists and social scientists in bringing in outside funds to support both
                     scholarly research and the overall operating costs of the institution. That these
                     grants are not always sufficient to create a project—requiring additional rounds of
                     grant funding—simply requires thinking of a project in stages and the occasionally
                     creative re-envisioning of a project.</p> 
                  <p>However, while short-term funding can support the creation of digital projects, it
                     fails to support the publishing and preservation stages of a project's lifecycle.
                     It's not uncommon for DH projects to vanish after five or ten years, as opposed to
                     traditional books and articles that could remain available for decades or even centuries.
                     A scholar’s responsibility to a book can end with initial publication and outreach,
                     but there is no digital equivalent to the legions of librarians who place books on
                     climate-controlled and secure shelves for access, repair the physical item when it
                     is damaged, and eventually determine if the item is worth long-term preservation in
                     a special collection or if it can be deaccessioned for lack of use. Sustaining or
                     preserving each individual digital project requires additional labor and funding,
                     which can last an indeterminate period of time. These long-term costs do not fit neatly
                     into a single grant cycle, prompting humanists to resort to increasingly creative
                     grant applications and fundraising to reinvent old projects, bury their heads in the
                     sand in denial, and/or accept the ephemerality of many (though not all) of the products
                     of their hard work.</p> 
                  <p>This essay will explore the role of soft and hard funding in the digital humanities,
                     with particular attention paid to the ways funding intersects with sustainability
                     and preservation. It will discuss a variety of types of soft funding available from
                     public, private, and institutional sources, and the ways the needs of funders can
                     align with or compete with the desires of scholars. The availability and sustainability
                     of funding as project needs change over time, along with funders' agendas, can influence
                     project teams' decisions about the direction a project will take, who leads it, who
                     can contribute to it, what technology supports it, on what severs it is hosted, if
                     and when it can be updated, as well as if and where it will be preserved. Not considering
                     the implications of financial support received can be detrimental to both the project
                     and the researchers involved. Seeking funding should become part of wider strategies
                     that enable the formation of mutually beneficial relationships, promising avenues
                     of research, and sustainable revenue streams, rather than a time sink that explodes
                     a project's scope in ways that undermine the project.</p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Jim McGrath: ‘Best Practices’: Some Perspectives on Collaboration and Project Development</summary> 
                  <p>The collaborative dimensions of many digital humanities projects are often complicated
                     and constrained by ideas of value and conditions of labor in higher education. Increasingly,
                     collaborative digital projects have made efforts to assemble core project teams that
                     grant agency and authority to the various people and professionals whose contributions
                     are essential to the success of these initiatives: students, community stakeholders,
                     librarians, archivists, programmers, designers, developers. But these forms of collaboration
                     are often varied, contentious, and messy, given that they span a range of different
                     professional contexts while operating within environments that traditionally privilege
                     and prioritize the roles and contributions of faculty members and their attendant
                     scholarly outputs like monographs and journal articles. It may be tempting to adopt
                     best practices and collaborative methodologies that prioritize cleaning up these particular
                     messes instead of addressing their implications. This talk hopefully steers us towards
                     other futures and possibilities for digital collaboration. For example, instead of
                     designing project roles and workflows that acknowledge the precarity of student and
                     postdoctoral labor in ways that privilege the longevity and endurance of a digital
                     project, what would it mean to center collaborative work on the interests, needs,
                     and aspirations of those particular contributors? Instead of prioritizing digital
                     projects initiated by tenure-track or tenured faculty, what would collaboration and
                     support look like if we deployed institutional and administrative resources to support
                     projects initiated by students, librarians, archivists, artists, community partners?
                     Instead of remediating academic investments in definitive, comprehensive, authoritative,
                     unified forms of publication in our ideas of digital projects with clear beginnings,
                     middles, and endings, what would it look like to create conditions of collaboration
                     that emphasized a wider range of possibilities?</p> 
                  <p>In this talk I will highlight the ways that the physical and textual records left
                     behind by a project — web sites, publications, citations, institutional forms of documentation,
                     digital assets secured for long-term preservation — can at times offer an incomplete
                     record and sanitized view of collaboration on digital initiatives, a perspective that
                     often reveals how particular collaborators are valued and treated by institutions
                     and professional networks beyond their immediate departments and campuses. I will
                     reflect on my experiences with collaboration in various project roles — graduate student,
                     postdoctoral fellow, instructor, consultant — and how these particular contexts have
                     informed my collaborative contributions and their reception. And I will discuss the
                     ways that arguments for <q>best practices</q> in project development, collaboration, and project endings are inevitably challenged
                     and complicated by the institutional and professional realities that shape the roles
                     of specific collaborators and their working conditions.</p> 
                  <p>My perspectives on collaboration draw on previous and ongoing efforts as a director
                     of digital projects, as a consultant on digital initiatives, as a frequent collaborator
                     with community partners, librarians, and archivists, and as an instructor specializing
                     in digital public humanities. These perspectives are also informed by the work of
                     Moya Bailey, Michelle Caswell, Marika Cifor, Julia Flanders, Paige Morgan, and Jentery
                     Sayers, among others. I will discuss the role of graduate labor on Our Marathon: The
                     Boston Bombing Digital Archive and the ways that project’s ideas of labor, forms of
                     institutional support, ideas of audience, and investments in crowdsourcing variously
                     shaped its development, accomplishments, and ending. I will highlight aspects of my
                     ongoing work on Mapping Violence, a digital initiative that relies heavily on undergraduate
                     labor and collaboration, that is informed by relationships with community stakeholders,
                     that complements non-digital forms of public history and advocacy, and that aspires
                     to self-reflective, iterative, and slower forms of collaboration and project development.
                     And I will talk about my role as a postdoctoral fellow in an American Studies department
                     and Public Humanities graduate program: my approach to designing courses that create
                     opportunities for collaboration and project prototyping, my roles on digital initiatives
                     created in collaboration with community partners, and the ways that my status as a
                     postdoc has shaped (and, at times, constrained) my abilities to develop, support,
                     and collaborate on digital projects.</p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Nick Thieberger: Doing it for ourselves: The new archive built by and reponsive to
                     the researcher</summary> 
                  <p>We are at a turning point in the preservation of analog media. Experts predict that
                     analog tapes will be unplayable by the year 2025. Much of the primary research data
                     of linguistics, musicology, and anthropology is still located on this media and, in
                     many places, the task of preservation and repatriation of the content remains to be
                     taken up. Our research group, based at three Australian universities, addressed this
                     challenge in the early 2000s, building a repository and digitisation workflow that
                     now includes 115 terabytes of material, representing 1,267 languages in 14,000 hours
                     of audio recordings along with manuscript and video materials. In the course of doing
                     this, we train new researchers in appropriate methods for creating reusable primary
                     records, and built a platform for citation of data, allowing verifiability and, more
                     importantly, reuse of that data. We have done this with several 1-year infrastructure
                     grants over the 18-year life of the project. While there was an Australian National
                     Data Service, it paradoxically did not store data, and the current version, the Australian
                     Research Data Commons, also has no national service for curating research data ( and
                     so, no ‘Commons’|). So, despite large funding sources apparently available for research
                     data, it is typically not available for the kinds of humanities records we are concerned
                     with. More frustrating is the refrain that humanities researchers receive from national
                     research funders that we are unable to articulate our infrastructure needs.</p> 
                  <p>In the absence of institutional or national work to preserve the outputs of research
                     in our disciplines, our project, the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources
                     in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC), has developed exemplary methods and services based
                     on accepted standards for metadata and data formats. We have trained a new generation
                     of researchers, especially in our work as the repository for the ARC Centre of Excellence
                     for the Dynamics of Language. We act as a repository that curates and preserves research
                     at all stages of its creation: recordings deposited during fieldwork, or at the end
                     of a research project or a researcher’s career (or life). To support longevity we
                     have always written an XML file of the complete catalog entry to the item (the files),
                     so each item is self-describing. We are now building an OCFL (Oxford Common File Layout)
                     version which reduces dependence on monolithic databases to interpret the items and
                     their metadata. This allows us to build microservices for viewing items, and to develop
                     more meaningful ways of returning files to source communities, together with contextual
                     metadata.</p> 
                  <p>And, perhaps more important than any of this, digitisation has allowed us to engage
                     with the communities in the Pacific, PNG and South-East Asia, that are the source
                     of the recordings we can now return, half a century or more after they were made.</p> 
                  <p>I will show that a repository for primary research data has four major benefits:</p> 
                  <ul> 
                     <li>Citability of research data for verifiability/replicability of research claims</li> 
                     <li>Provision of a curated corpus of data for reuse</li> 
                     <li>Establishing a home for end-of-life research materials</li> 
                     <li>Licensed access to records for the people recorded, their communities, and their descendants,
                        thus mitigating the earlier perception of academics ‘stealing the data’.</li> </ul> 
                  <p>References</p> 
                  <p>Nick Thieberger. 2016. What remains to be done – Exposing invisible collections in
                     the other 7000 languages and why it is a DH enterprise. In <i>Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</i>. 32(2), 1:423–434. <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw006">http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw006</a></p> 
                  <p>Nick Thieberger &amp; Linda Barwick. 2012. Keeping records of language diversity in Melanesia,
                     the Pacific and Regional Archive for Digital Sources in Endangered Cultures (PARADISEC),
                     pp. 239-253 in Nicholas Evans &amp; Marian Klamer (Eds). <i>Melanesian languages on the edge of Asia: Challenges for the 21st Century</i>. LD&amp;C Special Publication No. 5. Honolulu: University of Hawai'i Press. <a href="http://scholarspace.manoa.hawaii.edu/handle/10125/4567">http://scholarspace.manoa.hawaii.edu/handle/10125/4567</a></p> </details> 
               <details> 
                  <summary>Claire Battershill: The Preservation of Critical Digital Archives: Obstacles and Affordances</summary> 
                  <p>Digital humanities projects often begin with specific scholarly goals in mind, whether
                     these goals are editorial, theoretical, archival, or methodological. When projects
                     begin, all is promise, potential, and excitement. The grant funding structure on which
                     many projects are founded also demands that projects begin with an optimistic view
                     and a future-oriented perspective. A team dreams up a vision and creates a plan for
                     executing it, and it’s difficult both practically and epistemologically to think about
                     an ending while constructing a beginning. Often these projects begin in heightened
                     moments of collegiality, collaboration, and shared vision among scholars; they’re
                     premised on new and exciting relationships as much as they are on research materials
                     and scholarly goals. They’re also often labours of love. This discussion will focus
                     on digital preservation as it concerns researchers: their own careers, their scholarly
                     aspirations and their collegial relationships with one another. I will draw in my
                     remarks from my own experience and will contrast two projects with two very different
                     approaches to endings: one ongoing collaborative digital endeavour, the Modernist
                     Archives Publishing Project (MAPP), and one grant-funded, constrained exhibition project,
                     Make Believe, which had a clear and limited trajectory and timeline and a definite
                     end-point. I will focus here on the narrative and affective dimensions of digital
                     project life cycles. What does it feel like to talk about endings, especially among
                     close-knit scholarly teams who have collaborated for years?</p> 
                  <p>A digital project is born, and then its life proceeds and gets complicated. Of course,
                     as project teams devise digital methods for exploring humanistic questions, they are
                     often confronted with challenges and opportunities they would not have encountered
                     were they writing a single-author monograph or creating a print edition. One such
                     challenge, as the Project Endings teams acknowledges, is defining the endpoint of
                     the project in a digital environment that is by nature iterative and surrounded by
                     a mythology of ongoingness and perpetuity. The print publishing process, conversely,
                     naturally produces a moment of completion: a book is published and then it is out
                     in the world and often that’s the end of the active day-to-day work on that particular
                     project. The developmental arc of the monograph is so well-established at this point
                     that we’re used to it; it doesn’t possess the complexity as discussions of digital
                     project endings. Much as the author might wish to continue to revise and augment the
                     book after it’s done, the fixity of the printed object at least imposes an artificial
                     endpoint on the active work of the project. The existence of a physical object can
                     also seem more definitive than any ending a digital project might devise or arrange
                     for itself. The milestones in the life of a digital project — the launch of a website,
                     say — are often possessed of a more malleable quality. One often launches a website
                     with the idea that it will change and grow over time.</p> 
                  <p>However, the discourses of ongoingness and iteration in digital project work, while
                     they do point to a truth about the type of media in question, have their limits. As
                     digital project team members move through their careers – from PhD to postdoc to demanding
                     jobs both within and outside the academy — finding space for an ever-expanding and
                     ever-continuing digital project within the team members’ individual careers can be
                     a further challenge. Grant cycles come to an end, program centres open and close,
                     and resources run out. Thinking about the long life of a project is twinned with thinking
                     about the long future of an academic career, and even, these days, of the discipline.
                     Thinking about these matters requires a multi-dimensional approach: we need to think
                     beyond institutional repositories and mirror sites and consider the lived experience
                     of project making and about the structure of the stories we tell about digital work.</p> </details>
    </main>
</body>
