<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Why do I need four search engines?</title>

            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Martin</forename>
                  <surname>Holmes</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>University of Victoria</affiliation>
               <email>mholmes@uvic.ca</email>
            </author>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname>Takeda</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
               <email>joey.takeda@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>JADH</publisher>
            <date/>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The Japanese Association for Digital Humanities 2018 Conference, Tokyo, Japan.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>archiving</term>
               <term>digital editions</term>
               <term>preservation</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This presentation addresses the question of how to create digital editions and 
            other online resources in forms that are likely to endure and remain functional over many decades. In particular,
            we focus on the dichotomy whereby the long-term robustness of a digital project, which is achieved by 
            uncoupling it from transient server-side technologies and tools that require monitoring and maintenance,
            is undermined by the requirement to provide methods for users to search the collection. We present as a 
            case-study the <title level="m">Robert Graves Diary</title> project, which provides four separate search
            facilities using different approaches.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>

         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p> Project Endings<note><ref target="https://github.com/projectEndings"
                     >https://github.com/projectEndings</ref>, <ref
                     target="https://onlineacademiccommunity.uvic.ca/endingsproject/"
                     >https://onlineacademiccommunity.uvic.ca/endingsproject/</ref></note> is a
               collaboration of University of Victoria scholars, digital humanists and librarians
               whose aim is to address the progressive loss of digital scholarly resources due to
               failures in archiving, preservation, and documentation, and over-dependence on
               transient tools and technologies. The project is supported by a grant from the Social
               Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada (<ref
                  target="http://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/">SSHRC</ref>). </p>

            <p>The project is working with a number of case-studies—digital edition projects already
               completed or nearing completion—and aiming to specify approaches, tools and
               technologies that can help researchers complete their projects and archive them in
               such a way that they have a strong chance of being available and functional for
               decades to come.</p>

            <p>In previous work (<ref type="bibl" target="#arneil_holmes_2017">Arneil and Holmes
                  2017</ref>, <ref type="bibl" target="#holmes_2017">Holmes 2017</ref>, <ref
                  type="bibl" target="#holmes_takeda_2017">Holmes and Takeda 2017</ref>), we have
               argued strongly that likelihood that a digital edition project will survive and be
               usable over the long term depends on the selection of a small core set of
               technologies (HTML5, CSS and JavaScript), and the avoidance of server-side
               technologies that will require maintenance or replacement over time. Our case-study
               projects (among them <title level="m"><ref target="http://mariage/uvic.ca/">Le
                     Mariage sous L’Ancien Régime</ref></title> and <title level="m"><ref
                     target="http://graves.uvic.ca/">The Robert Graves Diary</ref></title>) are
               constructed entirely in this way, with no server-side dependencies at all. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="search">
            <head>The problem of search</head>

            <p>A digital edition consisting only of HTML, CSS and JavaScript can of course be rich
               and highly interactive. However, there is one important component of a website which
               generally requires some sort of server interaction: search. This is perhaps the most
               difficult challenge for the Endings project: how do we make a resource searchable
               without building in dependence on a server to host the index and respond to
               queries?</p>
            
            <figure xml:id="fig1">
               <graphic url="images/graves_search.png" width="1104px" height="570px"/>
               <head type="legend">The first search interface of the Robert Graves Diary, which
               also serves as its home page.</head>
            </figure>

            <p>Using the <title level="m">Robert Graves Diary</title> project as a testbed, we have
               developed four distinct approaches, which will be described in this presentation:</p>

            <list rend="ordered">
               <item><emph>Bite the bullet and accept the server dependency.</emph> We currently
                  host the Graves project materials inside an eXist XML database, which allows us to
                  provide rich faceted search functionality at the expense of a dependency that will
                  inevitably be unsupported in the long term.</item>
               <item><emph>Enlist Google’s help.</emph> We have built an additional Google Custom
                  Search page into the site, allowing users to search in the interface which is
                  probably most familiar to them. The obvious drawback here is that Google’s terms,
                  conditions and APIs change frequently, so we must expect this service to fail at
                  some point when there is no active maintainer of the project.</item>
               <item><emph>Enlist the help of our Library.</emph> The long-term preservation of our
                  project will ultimately be in the hands of the University Library, who run their
                  own Solr server for searching their collections. As part of the project build, we
                  now create JSON index files for Solr to ingest; we can then provide a search page
                  which queries this index.</item>
               <item><emph>Provide a standalone search.</emph> For digital editions which are not
                  too large, it is possible to create a JavaScript-only index, including stemming
                  and relevance scoring, which is remarkably fast and requires no server support at
                  all. This is the ultimate fallback when all else fails.</item>
            </list>

            <p>On the face of it, this level of redundancy may appear ridiculous, but in fact it provides
            a level of flexibility which we believe is essential for the survival of 
            projects with no ongoing maintenance. In the best-case scenario, four different methods
            of searching the collection are available to the user, each with their own strengths
            and weaknesses. In the worst case, where the collection survives only as a simple
            collection of files on a drive somewhere, the standalone search will still work, 
            while the other non-functional search interfaces provide evidence of the aspects of
            the collection thought to be crucial search facets. </p>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">

            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="arneil_holmes_2017"><author>Arneil, Stewart</author> and <author>Martin
                     Holmes</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Archiving form and
                     function: preserving a 2003 digital project</title>. DPASSH Conference 2017:
                  Digital Preservation for Social Sciences and Humanities, Brighton, UK, 14th June
                  2018. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_2017"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title
                     level="a">Selecting Technologies for Long-Term Survival</title>. SHARP
                  Conference 2017: Technologies of the Book, Victoria, BC, Canada, 10th June 2017.
                     <ref
                     target="https://github.com/projectEndings/Endings/raw/master/presentations/SHARP_2017/mdh_sharp_2017.pdf"
                     >https://github.com/projectEndings/Endings/raw/master/presentations/SHARP_2017/mdh_sharp_2017.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="holmes_takeda_2017"><author>Holmes, Martin</author> and <author>Joseph
                     Takeda</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">Beyond Validation: Using
                     Programmed Diagnostics to Learn About, Monitor, and Successfully Complete Your
                     DH Project</title>. Digital Humanities 2017 Conference, Montreal, Canada, 1th
                  August 2017. <ref target="https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/140/140.pdf"
                     >https://dh2017.adho.org/abstracts/140/140.pdf</ref>.</bibl>

            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
